<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The church-catechism enlarg'd and explain'd in an easie and familiar method, with the scripture-proofs annexed thereunto.</title>
            <author>R. M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M70A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833042</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833042</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37517</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52008)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37517)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2190:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The church-catechism enlarg'd and explain'd in an easie and familiar method, with the scripture-proofs annexed thereunto.</title>
                  <author>R. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>62, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Parkhurst, at the Bible and Three Crowns, at the lower end of Cheapside, near Mercers Chappel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: R.M.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisment leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Dr. William's Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37517:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37517:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Church-Catechiſm</hi> ENLARG'D and EXPLAIN'D, IN AN Eaſie and Familiar METHOD, WITH THE <hi>SCRIPTURE-PROOFS</hi> Annexed thereunto.</p>
            <q>Theſe words which I command thee this day ſhall be in thine Heart. And thou ſhalt teach them diligently unto thy Children, and ſhalt talk of them when thou ſitteſt in thy houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lyeſt down, and when thou riſeſt up. <bibl>Deut. 6.7, 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> Thomas Parkhurſt, <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three Crowns, <hi>at the lower end of</hi> Cheapſide, <hi>near</hi> Mercers <hi>Chappel. 1697.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:37517:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37517:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THIS explication of the Catechiſm ſuppoſeth the Reader to be convinc'd of the neceſſity and excellency of the Duty of Catechizing; and the great danger of the neglect thereof, in Churches or Familys where there are any that need training up in the way that they ſhould go.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that there are many who have written ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently on the Catechiſm; and no wonder, when ſo much of every Miniſters time is or ought to be taken up in the uſe of it. But yet there are not many that have made uſe of this Method; The firſt Deſigner of it, being taken away, as is ſaid in his life, before He had accompliſh't what He intended, was followed by Doctor <hi>Wallis</hi> upon another <hi>Catechiſm:</hi> Doctor <hi>Comber,</hi> and (I think) He a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone followed him upon <hi>this:</hi> yet He by deſigning ſo much brevity and altogether omitting the Scripture proofs hath left room for a further Eſſay.</p>
            <p>The uſe of this Mothod is double. (<hi>1.</hi>) As to the meaneſt capacitys it hath a viſible benefit, in that the Queſtion is ſo fram'd as to lead the perſon inſtructed to his Anſwer, whereby his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is both try'd and inform'd and yet the memory not bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd with words; it being evident that many of the more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſort are frighted from the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> by a long Anſwer impos'd upon the memory: and others get words by vote which they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not and preſently ſinger. I only here deſire of the Teacher, that when He propounds or as be any Queſtion, He would not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs or recite the Text or Texts of Scripture annexed thereunto; partly becauſe theſe proofs do indeed belong to the Anſwer, and not to the Queſtion, though they could not conveniently be places
<pb facs="tcp:37517:3"/>otherwiſe than they are; and partly, becauſe ſuch a recital of the Texts, Chapter and Verſe would make the Queſtion ſo long as to hinder the attention of the Learner: great care being to be taken that He Anſwers underſtandingly, and not by gheſs, <hi>Yes</hi> or <hi>No:</hi> and for that reaſon He may ſometimes be required to repeat the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Queſtion in his Anſwer; as Q. <hi>Are there more Gods than One?</hi> A. <hi>No, there are not more Gods than One. (2.)</hi> The other uſe is for them that have more underſtanding, who muſt be obliged to anſwer to the Queſtion, by the Scripture annexed; in this manner. Q. <hi>Are there more Gods than One?</hi> A. <hi>No.</hi> Q. <hi>How prove you that?</hi> A. <hi>From Deut. 6.4. Hear O Iſrael the Lord thy God is one Lord,</hi> and I think, it cannot be deny'd, that the beſt as well as eaſieſt way of Learning Scripture-principles is in Scripture Phraſe. Thoſe lively Oracles make a deeper and more abiding impreſſion than any other words: And the prudent Catechiſt may with his Pen mark in every Section ſuch Texts for the Learner to recite at a time as He ſhall judge for plainneſs or number to be ſuited to his Capacity.</p>
            <p>Nor will this hinder the Learning theſe Principles in diſtinct pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions as they are ſet down in other <hi>Catechiſms;</hi> but will make it far more eaſie to Learn the words, when they are by this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed beforehand in the matter therein contain'd.</p>
            <p>In this Compoſure I have endeavoured to make the Queſtions very Comprehenſive, by crowding thereinto as much matter, as would conſiſt with the plainneſs that I ſtudiouſly deſign'd: ſo that there is enough in each <hi>Queſtion,</hi> eſpecially when the <hi>proof</hi> is given in <hi>Anſwer,</hi> for the Catechiſt to dilate and enlarge upon, in his more Familiar Inſtructing of thoſe committed to his Charge.</p>
            <p>May the whole be for the Glory of God through Christ, and for the Edification of his Flock, particularly the Lambs therein.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37517:3"/>
            <head>A <hi>CATECHISM:</hi> That is to ſay, An Inſtruction to be learned of every Perſon before He be brought to be Confirmed by the Biſhop.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHat is your Name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>N. <hi>or</hi> M.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who gave you this Name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Godfathers and Godmothers in my Baptiſm, wherein I was made a Member of Chriſt, the Child of God, and an Inheritor of the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. WAS not your Name given you at your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as they were wont to receive their Names at their Circumciſion? <hi>Luke</hi> 2.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it not in the power of Parents (chiefly of Fathers) to give Names to their Children? <hi>Luke</hi> 1.60, 62.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it then unlawful for others, by the Parents Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to do it, as Godfathers and Godmothers amongſt us? <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE Infants incapable of receiving any Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges or Benefits by Baptiſm? <hi>Mark</hi> 10.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(1.) Are there not certain <hi>outward</hi> Priviledges <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd</hi> by Baptiſm, as of old, by Circumciſion? <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Were you not by Baptiſm made <hi>a Member of Chriſt, i. e.</hi> of his Body, the Church? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15. &amp; 12.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But have all ſuch Members of Chriſt a ſaving intereſt in him, or benefit by him? <hi>John</hi> 15.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* VVere you not thereby made the <hi>Child of God? Acts</hi> 3.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:37517:4"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And are there not many viſible Children of God, that prove rebels againſt him? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* VVere you not further admitted an Heir, or <hi>inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritour of the Kingdom of Heaven? Eph.</hi> 3.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And are there not many viſible Heirs or <hi>Children of the Kingdom</hi> that ſhall be caſt out? <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Is there then any Reaſon why they that live in Sin, ſhould boaſt of, or reſt in, theſe outward Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges? <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(2.) Are there not alſo inward and ſpiritual privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges offered in Baptiſm, and ſealed on Gods part to Believers? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26, 27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are theſe beſtowed on you without any Conditions required on your part? <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do the conditions and terms of the Goſpel make the Grace therein not to be free? <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Are you not then by Baptiſm under an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to perform the Goſpel-conditions? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What did your Godfathers and Godmothers then for you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They did promiſe and vow thrée things in my Name;</hi> Firſt, <hi>That I ſhould renounce the Devil and all his Works, the Pomps and Vanity of this wicked World, and all the ſinful Luſts of the Fleſh.</hi> Secondly, <hi>That I ſhould believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith. And</hi> Thirdly, <hi>That I ſhould keep Gods holy Will and Commandments, and walk in the ſame all the days of my Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DID your Sureties ſay, when you were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, that you did ſo repent and believe?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did they promiſe in <hi>their own Name,</hi> or bind their own Souls with a Vow, that you ſhould do ſo when you came to Age?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did they not then <hi>in your Name</hi> promiſe, or declare the Vow that you ſhould be bound to perform? <hi>Luke</hi> 5.18-20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>If you had been Baptized at Age, ſhould you not <hi>in your own Name</hi> have made the Promiſe?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† VVhoever then made the Profeſſion <hi>in your Name,</hi>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37517:4"/>do you not now acknowledge it was <hi>your</hi> Promiſe and <hi>your</hi> Vow? <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.106.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the Baptiſmal Vow to <hi>Renounce</hi> and forſake all your Spiritual Enemies?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(1.) Muſt you not <hi>Renounce the Devil,</hi> under whoſe Power you were by Nature? <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it enough to Renounce the Worſhip of the Devil, which is practiſed by Idolaters, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20, and by Wizards and Charmers? <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10, 11, 12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt you not renounce and reſiſt him as an Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and a tempter, <hi>with all his works? Jam.</hi> 4.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt you not renounce the Suggeſtions of Satan and his inſtruments, which are the <hi>works</hi> that He practiſeth for your ruin? <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt you not renounce the <hi>works</hi> that Signally bear the Devils Image, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8. Such as, Lying. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44. pride. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. Malice. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.26, 27. Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.70, 71. and the Seducing others. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.10?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(2.) Is not the world another Enemy that you are bound to renounce? <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are you bound to leave the Society of men, and to dwell alone in woods and rocks; or to renounce your Callings and Eſtates, and vow Poverty? <hi>Acts</hi> 20.35.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not renounce the examples, flatterys and enticings of wicked men? <hi>Rom.</hi> 12 2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May we then like the Company, or have a voluntary Fellowſhip with notoriouſly ungodly men? <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not renounce the things of the <hi>world,</hi> ſo far as they are contrary to Chriſt, or would draw us from him? <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did not the firſt Chriſtians renounce by the name of Pomps and Vanities, the <hi>Pompous</hi> ſhews in the Pagan Theatres and Proceſſions?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we then be allowed to frequent prophane Stage-plays, or the revels in Wakes and drunken Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals? <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we immoderately or unſeaſonably ſeek or affect the riches, honours, or pleaſures of the <hi>world?</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.15, 16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(3.) Is not the <hi>fleſh</hi> with <hi>the ſinful luſts</hi> thereof the other enemy that we muſt renounce? <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not original Sin and corruption the fountain of all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37517:5"/>actual Sins call'd the <hi>works of the fleſh?</hi> Jam. 1.14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19-22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth it no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>luſt</hi> againſt the Spirit and draw even the Members of the body to Sin? <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we then follow the depraved dictates and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings of <hi>a fleſhly mind? Rom.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not eſpecially abhor the groſs ſins, and <hi>fleſhly luſts</hi> that War againſt the Soul? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE we not to obſerve in our Baptiſmal Vow, what we are to <hi>believe,</hi> as well as what we are to <hi>renounce?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. Are not the Holy Scriptures, (<hi>Acts</hi> 24.14.) and particularly the Articles of the Creed, the <hi>Doctrinal</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our Faith? <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can we believe theſe without underſtanding their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſome good eſteem of their excellency? <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not aſſent to the truth of theſe Articles, and live and dye in contending for the Faith? <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. <hi>Jud.</hi> 3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it enough to profeſs theſe Doctrines with the mouth, without believing with the Heart? <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9, 10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it enough to believe them implicitly, becauſe the Church believes them, without ever examining and trying them by the word? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not believe with application to our Hearts, particularly in what relates to Chriſt? <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. Is not Chriſt Himſelf then, the immediate and <hi>Perſonal</hi> Object of our Faith, as a Mediator, appointed by God, and dying for us? <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not Faith to receive Chriſt as offer'd in the Goſpel, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. and to rely on his merits and righteouſneſs?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it enough then to aſſent to the Articles as true, without a conſent to the offers and terms of the Goſpel? <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19, 20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not ſaving Faith wrought powerfully by the Spirit. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19. and doth it not work by love and all good fruits? <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is Faith then a ſtrong conceit or perſwaſion that Chriſt dy'd for you, though you live in ſin and were never humbled for it? <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22, 23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE we not further engag'd by the Baptiſmal Vow to a continual obedience to the Holy will of God?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37517:5"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did you promiſe a <hi>ſinleſs</hi> Obedience, for the ends of the Covenant of Works? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But is not <hi>ſincere</hi> Obedience to the will of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in his word, indiſpenſably required in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace? <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not this new Obedience from the efficacy of the Spirit, and conſtraint of Divine Love? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet are we forbidden to take Motives of our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from fear of puniſhment or hope of reward? <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are not the ends of it, that God may be glorify'd. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. Our Neighbour edify'd. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1, 2. and our Selves made meet for Heaven? <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Will God then accept of that partial Obedience, that comes from meer cuſtom and Education, and is done for ſelf-applauſe or pretence of merit? <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt not our Obedience be free and willing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being griev'd at any of his Commands? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt it not be univerſal, with <hi>all</hi> the Heart, and with a reſpect to <hi>all</hi> his Commandments, and that in <hi>all</hi> our actions? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.128. <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt it not be conſtant, even <hi>all the days of our Lives? Luk.</hi> 1.74, 75.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doſt thou think that thou art bound to believe and to do, as they have promis'd for thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yes verily; and by God's help ſo I will, and I heartily thank our Heavenly Father, that He hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me to this State of Salvation, through Ieſus Chriſt our Saviour, and I pray unto God to give me his Grace, that I may continue in the ſame to my lives end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. HAVE you conſidered your Solemn Vow and Promiſe made in Baptiſm? <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.28, 31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do you now in the preſence of God and this Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation make a profeſſion of your ſtanding to your Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Covenant? <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.22, 27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* You ſay <hi>you will</hi> now; but will you make this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37517:6"/>in the moſt difficult and coſtly circumſtances, when the glory of God is concern'd? <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.3, 4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Do you make this profeſſion only for hereafter, without ſetting about the performance preſently? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.60.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>You ſay, <hi>you will,</hi> but can you do it, in your own ſtrength? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Do you then profeſs this, in and by the <hi>help,</hi> ſtrength and aſſiſtance of God? <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And is God wanting to his Church as to ſufficiency of means for your help therein? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE all that live under the Goſpel <hi>outwardly called to the State of Salvation</hi> and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the means? <hi>Acts</hi> 13.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are all under this common <hi>call,</hi> alſo called effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and choſen? <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But can this <hi>outward call</hi> be refus'd, without the woful hazard of the Soul? <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24, 26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the Goſpel-call a great priviledge; and muſt you not Solemnly <hi>thank God our Heavenly Father through Chriſt for it? Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is there not great danger of being drawn from the <hi>State</hi> to which you are <hi>called,</hi> by damnable doctrines or practices? <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can you <hi>then continue therein</hi> and be kept from revolting from your profeſſion without real <hi>grace? Heb.</hi> 13.9. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12, 13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And if God gives you the firſt <hi>grace,</hi> is perſeverance therein of your Selves? <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.32.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. WILL you then <hi>pray unto God for his Grace</hi> to prevent, and aſſiſt you and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate at laſt his work in you? <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And muſt you not to prayer add the diligent uſe of all the means, that God has appointed? <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.29.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are you willing for your further help, that I ſhould teach you what you are to believe and to do according to your promiſe? <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Catechiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rehearſe the Articles of thy Belief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37517:6"/>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>Believe in God the Father Almighty, maker of Heaven and Earth: And in Ieſus Chriſt his only Son our Lord, Who was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, Born of the Virgin Mary, Suffered under Pontius Pilate, Was crucifyed, dead and buried, he deſcended into Hell, The third day he roſe again from the dead, He aſcended into Heaven, And ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father Almighty, From thence he ſhall come to judge the Quick and the Dead. I believe in the Holy Ghoſt, The Holy Catholick Church, the Communion of Saints, The forgiveneſs of Sins, The reſurrection of the body, And the life everlaſting. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS this Creed found in ſo many words, any where, in Scripture?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet is not the whole of it proved by Scripture, as being according to the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, and therefore called the Apoſiles Creed? <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it not agreeable to Scripture that there ſhould be ſuch a Form of ſound Words? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we receive any thing as an Article of Faith that is not found in Scripture? <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not all things revealed in the Scriptures, to be believed by us? <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But are all things therein alike neceſſary to be known? <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are not all things neceſſary and Fundamental plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly revealed? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.105.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Were not the Scriptures confirm'd by Miracles, own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Church in all Ages; and are they not known by their majeſty, purity, and efficacy on the Hearts of Believers? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7, 8, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Will you not then ſearch the Scriptures to prove the Articles of your Belief? <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the firſt Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>I believe in God the Father Almighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not <hi>Believing in God</hi> denote a practical truſting in, and depending on Father Son and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37517:7"/>Holy Ghoſt, as our Father, Redeemer and Sanctifyer?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can this be without underſtanding what God hath revealed concerning himſelf, as ſtanding in theſe Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to us? <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DO you not believe that there is a God, a moſt pure and ſupream Spirit? <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hath He a body or bodily parts, or can He be ſeen with mortal eyes? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is He not infinite in his being and bleſſedneſs? <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is He confin'd to Time or place? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.1. or doth He ſtand in need of any of his Creatures to make Him happy? <hi>Acts</hi> 17.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is He ſubject to change or alteration? <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can his attributes and glorious perfections be fully comprehended by us? <hi>Job</hi> 11.7, 8, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is He not moſt Holy, Powerful, Wiſe, Good, Juſt and true; and this Originally and independently ſo as no Creature can be? <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE there more Gods than One? <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4. Is it agreeable to right reaſon that there ſhould be more than one firſt Cauſe, on which all things depend? <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE there not three Perſons in the Godhead, the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghoſt? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is either of theſe Divine Perſons before or after, greater or leſs than the other? <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.30.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Have they not one and the ſame Divine nature, and are they not diſtinguiſhed by their Perſonal properties?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did not the Father from eternity beget the Son, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.7. and is not the Son begotten of the Father before all worlds? <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth not the Holy Ghoſt proceed from the Father and the Son? <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DID not the <hi>Almighty</hi> power of God appear in the works of his Creation? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.12, 13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Did He not make all things of nothing, by the word of his power, in the ſpace of 6 days? <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37517:7"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did He make any thing amiſs? <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† And doth He not by his providence uphold and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern all that He hath made? <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Did He not in particular make man, his body Form'd of the duſt, and his Soul immediately inſpir'd? <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did not God create him after his own Image, a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, holy creature, able alſo to ſulfil the whole Law? <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did not God Covenant with man to confirm his life and happineſs, upon condition of his perfect obedience? <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was the particular command given to try his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience (<hi>viz.</hi> that He ſhould not eat of the tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and evil) a hard and impoſſible thing?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did not God threaten death on his diſobedience. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Should man have dy'd, if he had not ſinned. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did not man underſtand and agree to his Covenant? <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Second Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>And in Jeſus Chriſt His only Son, our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DO you not Believe in God the Son, the Second Perſon of the Trinity, equal with the Father and partaker of the ſame eſſence? <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Though Believers are called Sons by Grace and adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1. Yet is not our Lord <hi>His only Son</hi> by Nature and Eternal Generation? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the Son of God called <hi>Jeſus</hi> becauſe He ſaves his People from their Sins? <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was man confirm'd in the holy eſtate in which He was created, as the Elect Angels are now?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did He not fall from that eſtate by Tranſgreſſing the Law and command which God gave him? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.29.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did He not Sin by the temptation of the Devil, being left to the freedom of his own will? <hi>Gen.</hi> 3 4, 5, 6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can ſo high an affront to the majeſty of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, that contain'd ſo much Infidelity and ſuch a total defection from God, be reckoned a ſmall Sin?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37517:8"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was not <hi>Adam</hi> our common Father, a publick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and our Repreſentative in the Covenant of works? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12, 19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are there then any meer men that are not guilty of <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt ſin, and lyable to wrath thereupon? <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not our nature by the fall corrupted by Original Sin, from whence all actual Tranſgreſſions flow? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And is there any ſin that doth not deſerve death and eternal Damnation? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Has God left all the poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> to periſh in this State, into which they brought themſelves?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Having choſen ſome before all time. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4. hath He not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>red into a new Covenant with them, called the Covenant of Grace? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is man left to ſave Himſelf by his own wiſdom or power? <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Or, is there any other Redeemer from this State of ſin and wrath, but our Lord Jeſus Chriſt? <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Did not the Son of God that He might Redeem us, become man and take on him a true body and reaſonable Soul? <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is He not then one Perſon in two Natures?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>If He had not been man could He have dyed, and if He had not been God could he have Merited by dying? <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not this Jeſus the <hi>Chriſt</hi> or <hi>Meſſias,</hi> ſo long promiſed and expected? <hi>Job.</hi> 8.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is He not called <hi>Chriſt</hi> becauſe anointed to His Offices by the Spirit, which He received without meaſure? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.34.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(1.) Were not Prophets anointed. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.16. and had not He the Office of a <hi>Prophet? Acts</hi> 3.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Could we have known the will of God, if his only begotten Son had not revealed it? <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did He not at firſt preach himſelf, and afterwards ſend Paſtors and Teachers, to ſhew us the whole counſel of God touching our Salvation? <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But is the outward Preaching ſufficient without the inward effectual Teachings of the Spirit? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.45.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(2.) Were not the Legal Prieſts anointed. <hi>Exod.</hi> 40.13. and Hath not our Lord the Office of a <hi>Prieſt? Pſal.</hi> 110.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:37517:8"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was not his human nature, Soul and Body, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd up a Sacrifice to ſatisfie the Divine Juſtice? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13, 14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was this Sacrifice offer'd more than once; or, is it offer'd dayly in the Maſs? <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth He not now appear in Heaven to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for us? <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.24, 25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(3.) Were not Kings alſo anointed. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.1. and hath not He the Office of a <hi>King? Pſal.</hi> 2.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can any defend the Church, Deliver it, and Conquer the Enemies thereof but He? <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hath He not ſubdued Subjects to himſelf, erected Officers, and made Laws to govern his Church by? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is He not rightly Stiled <hi>Lord,</hi> as being rightful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign; and <hi>our Lord</hi> by right of Redemption, and our Reſignation of our Selves to him? <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Third Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Auſw. <hi>Who was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, born of the Virgin Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DID He take upon Him the nature of the Angels? <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Had He when He took our nature any earthly Father? <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was He not Conceived by the power of the Holy Ghoſt in the Womb of his Mother? <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did not the Holy Ghoſt by that wonderful operation, ſanctifie and purifie that Subſtance of the Virgin, of which He was made man? <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.35.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hath He then by taking on him the ſame Fleſh and Bloud that the Children have, the ſame Original Stain as they? <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And was not the Human Nature thus Form'd, in the moment of the Conception aſſum'd into the Perſon of the Son of God? <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.39.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did He relinquiſh his Divine Nature, or was there a Converſion of the Godhead into Fleſh? <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But did He not veil his Divinity, when in our Fleſh He ſeem'd to many, to be no more than a man? <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And is not this wonderful Condeſcenſion, called his <hi>coming down from Heaven</hi> for us? <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37517:9"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Are we capable of Comprehending fully the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Incarnation? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was it not according to the firſt promiſe, that He ſhould be <hi>the Seed of the Woman?</hi> Gen. 3.15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was He not born of a <hi>Virgin</hi> for further demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his power and purity? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And was He not born of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> as being of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> and Family of <hi>David? Rom.</hi> 1.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was there any thing in his Birth, as to time or place, which did not fully agree with the Prophecies that went before? <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was His Birth in Princes Courts or the ſplendour of Earthly Grandeut? <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.7</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet did not the Heavenly Hoſt, and miraculous Star declare his Dignity? <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Did He diſdain to be made under the Law, or to ſubmit to the Ceremonial part thereof, particularly in Circumciſion? <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4, 5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And was He not perfectly obedient to the whole moral Law? <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.15. and 5.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Fourth Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>He ſuffered under Pontius Pilate, was Crucified, Dead and buried, He deſcended into Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DID not our Lord Suffer the penalty of the Law for Sinners, as well as Submit to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of it? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was He not all his life time a Man of ſorrows, perſecuted, tempted, affronted, and Subject to all our natural and ſinleſs Infirmities? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet in the midſt of the Sufferings of his life, did He forbear to Preach, work Miracles, and to go about doing good? <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.38.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was He not betray'd, forſaken, and deny'd: reviled, ſpit on, and buffetted: accuſed, arraigned, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to death? <hi>Mat.</hi> 26 and 27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was it a ſmall matter that He ſuffered under Pontius Pilate (a man noted for cruelty? <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.1.) and by a Death which the <hi>Romans</hi> would inflict on none but their Slaves?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was not the Croſs a painful, lingering, ſhameful and accurſed death? <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* But was not his Soul-agony the bittereſt part of his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37517:9"/>Suffering both in the Garden and on the Croſs? <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.38. and 27.46.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did He not then, as the great propitiation, drink the Cup of Wrath, which we had deſerv'd? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6, 10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. WAS He not really <hi>dead</hi> by a Separation of his Soul from his body? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 19.3. <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.46.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Could He be otherwiſe than dead, when upon the piercing his ſide there came out forthwith bloud and water? <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.37.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did not the darkning of the Sun, the rending the Vail, the quaking of the Earth, and cleaving of the Rocks further confirm this tremendous myſtery? <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.51.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. AND could there be a greater evidence of his death, than his being <hi>buried,</hi> in ſuch a manner as is recorded? <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.59.—66.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yea, did not the place and circumſtances of his Burial contribute to the aſſurance of his following Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection? <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.39, 40.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MAY we doubt of the truth of his <hi>deſcending into Hell</hi> becauſe there are variety of opinions about the meaning of it?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>If upon his Reſurrection He <hi>was not left in Hell, Acts</hi> 2.30, 31. Is it not evident that He had firſt <hi>deſcended</hi> thither? <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it any where certainly revealed, that He went into the <hi>Hell</hi> of the damned, amongſt the Spirits there?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But did He not by his death vanquiſh the powers of Hell and darkneſs? <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not the unſeen State, or condition of ſeparation of Soul and Body, call'd the Grave and Hell? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And can it be deny'd that He ſo <hi>deſcended into Hell</hi> as to continue for a time under the dominion of Death in a ſeparate State? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Fifth Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>The third day He aroſe again from the Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:37517:10"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DID He <hi>always</hi> continue in that State of the dead, <hi>or ſo long</hi> as to ſee corruption? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Conſidering who He was, and what was Prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Him, was it poſſible for the bands of death to hold him? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did He not riſe again, by his own power? <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.17, 18. to dye no more? <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did He not riſe, as an evidence of our diſcharge <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. and a pledge of our Reſurrection? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Did He ſhew himſelf to all the people, when riſen, or to his enemies that had ſo long diſpiſed his miracles before? <hi>Acts</hi> 10.41.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet were they left altogether without convincing evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his Reſurrection? <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.2, 3, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was He not ſeen by a ſufficient number of witneſſes, (even 500 at once) and that at divers places and times, after He was riſen from the Dead? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Could they be deceiv'd by a Phantaſm or Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when they did both handle and ſee, yea eat and drink with Him after his Reſurrection? <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.38, 39.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Could ſo Miraculous a work as raiſing the Dead, for a deſign ſo contrary to Satan's Kingdom, be done by Magick or power of the Devil? <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19, 20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Could the Diſciples roll away the Stone from the Sepulchre, Steal away his Body, Strip it of the Grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloths, and not awake the Watch or Guard of Souldiers?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it likely that men noted for ſincerity, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. would impoſe on the world in a matter of ſuch conſequence, for which they expos'd themſelves to all manner of perſecutions and death it ſelf? <hi>Acts</hi> 5.41.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* If there had been any deceit could it have been conceal'd from ſo many envious and watchful enemies, in ſo publick a concern? <hi>Acts</hi> 26.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Did not the witneſſes of his Reſurrection confirm their report by undoubted Miracles? <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Was not this Reſurrection on <hi>the third day</hi> from his death, and <hi>the firſt day</hi> of the Week, which is our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Sabbath? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:37517:10"/>Qu. <hi>What is the Sixth Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>He aſcended into Heaven, And ſitteth on the Right Hand of God the Father Almighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. WHEN our Lord was riſen, Did He continue always on Earth in his bodily preſence? <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did He not according to Prophecy <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.18. Forty days after his Reſurrection, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.3. Aſcend up into Heaven in the ſight of his Diſciples? <hi>Acts</hi> 1.9— 11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was He not pleaſed to ſhew himſelf to ſome of his Diſciples after his aſcention? <hi>Acts</hi> 7.55. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Did He not Aſcend to prepare manſions for his people, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.2. and to ſend his Spirit to prepare them for the enjoyment thereof? <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are we to expect his bodily preſence any more on Earth, before the day of judgment? <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. BEING aſcended doth He not ſit at the Right Hand of God the Father Almighty? <hi>Mark</hi> 16.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth the <hi>Right Hand</hi> denote any bodily parts in God; or His <hi>ſitting</hi> any one particular geſture there? <hi>Acts</hi> 7.55.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth not <hi>ſitting</hi> down denote Reſt, and the <hi>Right Hand</hi> dignity and authority? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.3. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.30.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* And did not Chriſt after all his ſorrows on Earth, <hi>reſt</hi> in the unſpeakable joy of his Father? <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Hath He not the higheſt <hi>dignity</hi> and authority, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.4. and 8.1. and ſhall He not have compleat victory over all his Enemies? <hi>Pſal,</hi> 110.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Seventh Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>From thence He ſhall come to judge the Quick and the Dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. BEING thus exalted, Hath He for ever aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd this Earth and his people therein? <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Beſides his Spiritual preſence always with his Church, will He not come again in the clouds, as He was ſeen to go up? <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not this Second coming, to judge the world in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37517:11"/>righteouſneſs, and is not the day ſet and appointed for it? <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do we know the day and hour when this appointed judgment will be? <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.36.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. WILL He Judge them already <hi>Dead,</hi> and thoſe that are found <hi>Quick</hi> or alive at his coming? <hi>Acts</hi> 10.42.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>When all are gather'd before Him, will He not Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate between the Godly and the wicked and give to every Man according to his Works? <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.32. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Will it not be a <hi>day of refreſhing</hi> to the people of God, <hi>Acts.</hi> 3.19. and exceeding terrible to the wicked? 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shall any by power or policy be able to eſcape, or hide themſelves from the Judge? <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.15, 16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And muſt not all abide in that Condition to which they are adjudg'd for ever and ever? <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Eighth Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>I Believe in the Holy Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the Holy Ghoſt God, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.3, 4. Eternal, before the World, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. Omnipreſent, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7. and knowing all things? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not He a perſon, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2. diſtinct from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son? <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not He the Spirit of the Father, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.19. and of the Son, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. as proceeding from them both?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is He inferiour to the Father or Son in eſſence or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or with reſpect to the worſhip and glory which is due to God alone? <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS He not <hi>Holy</hi> in himſelf, and alſo as the Authour of <hi>Holineſs</hi> and Sanctification in us? <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Muſt we not then <hi>believe in</hi> Him as <hi>a ſanctifier</hi> by whom we may have an intereſt in what Chriſt has done and ſuffer'd?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are any partakers of ſaving Benefits by Chriſt, to whom they are not effectually apply'd or communicated? <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.11, 12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can Parents or Miniſters apply them to your Heart, or any but the Holy Spirit? <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5, 6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:37517:11"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth not the Spirit do this by working Faith in the Heart by the Miniſtry of the word? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44, 45.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth He not by the Law convince the Sinner, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8. and by the Goſpel ſubdue the will and perſwade it to yeild to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26, 27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can we then be ſav'd by Chriſt without effectual cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Regeneration by the Holy Ghoſt? <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Ninth Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. (I believe) <hi>the Holy Catholick Church, the Communion of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. HATH not God a <hi>Church called</hi> out of the world to be his peculiar people? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not believers a diſtinct Body or Society joyn'd to Chriſt by Faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23. and to each other by love? <hi>Col.</hi> 2.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can this Church be built on any other Head or founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than our Lord Jeſus Chriſt? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not part of this Church Triumphant in Heaven, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. and part Militant on Earth? <hi>Col.</hi> 1 24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is the Church known by external Splendour, Pomp, or Secular Grandeur? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not this Church <hi>Holy,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. the Saints above <hi>perfectly,</hi> and the effectually called <hi>really</hi> ſo?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not all the viſible Members thereof called to <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>Holy</hi> by profeſſion and obligation? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§ IS not the Church <hi>Catholick</hi> or Univerſal conſiſting of all Believers, <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Bond and Free? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is the Church confin'd to any one place or Nation? <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shall the Gates of Hell ever prevail againſt it? <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† May any of the particular Societys (of which it doth conſiſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20.) claim the name, Authority and priviledges of the Catholick Church? <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. AMONGST the many priviledges of the Church, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.3. is not this one, that there is <hi>the Communion of Saints?</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37517:12"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Have not Bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>vers Union and Communion with Chriſt their Head, from whence they are called <hi>Saints?</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do they not Communicate by Faith their wants to him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. and He by his Spirit Communicate his Merits and Grace to them? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.4. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And will he refuſe to ſuch, Communion with himſelf in Glory hereafter? <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Have not the Saints alſo Communion one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can they Communicate Merits to each other? <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.8, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Have not the Saints above Communion with each other in the ſame Viſion, Employment and Glory? <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Have not the Saints below Communion, in the ſame Gifts and Graces, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. in the ſame Sufferings, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.3. and if need be, in their Worldly goods? <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Tenth Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>The forgiveneſs of Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE there any Sins, Original or Actual, of Omiſſion or Commiſſion, of Thought, Word or Deed, that do not deſerve eternal Death? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet are there any that are not Pardonable (the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt only excepted?) <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth not forgiveneſs of Sins conſiſt in releaſing the Sinner from Guilt and Condemnation? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can any but God (who is the party offended) forgive Sins to Men? <hi>Pſal</hi> 51.4. <hi>Mark</hi> 2.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet muſt not all forgive injuries done to themſelves, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.21. and Miniſters Pronounce forgiveneſe in Chriſt's name to the Penitent? <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is there any forgiveneſs but only through Chriſt, and on the account of his Satisfaction? <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth the Satisfaction of Chriſt make forgiveneſs of Sins to be leſs Free and Gracious? <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Have any the actual forgiveneſs of their Sins be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they Repent and Believe? <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:37517:12"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Muſt you not then have a deep ſenſe of your Sins, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. Confeſs them to God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.5. with a ſincere Reſolution of forſaking them? <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt you not earneſtly make Supplication for Pardon, with a Fiducial truſt in the mercy of God, through the Merits and Righteouſneſs of Chriſt alone? <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Eleventh Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>The Reſurrection of the Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DID not death come in by Sin, as the Sentence of the Law for the Tranſgreſſion of it? <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can any of our Members, when turn'd to duſt and ſcatter'd, be hid from God's all-ſeeing Eye? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.15, 16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it above the Almighty power that made the Body at firſt of duſt, to raiſe it out of it again? <hi>Mark</hi> 12.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* And as He is able to raiſe the Dead, ſo are we to believe that He will do it? <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28, 29.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Though <hi>all</hi> ſhall be rais'd, the juſt and the unjuſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15. yet is not the Reſurrection the ſpecial Priviledge of Believers? <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Shall the Wicked riſe by vertue of an Union with Chriſt by his Spirit, as the Godly ſhall? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* And will there not be a vaſt difference between them in the ends for which they ariſe? <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it not agreeable to Divine Juſtice, that the ſame Bodies for ſubſtance, which we had here, ſhould be raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.38. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But will they be raiſed to the ſame dying and mortal State they were in before? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.53.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Will not the Bodies of the Saints be exceeding Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, of which the Reſurrection of Chriſt is both an aſſurance and a Pattern? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20, 43, 44.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† And ſhall not they who are found alive at the coming of Chriſt be alſo chang'd? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51, 52.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Twelfth Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>The life Everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. SHALL not Believers have a Life of Glory and happineſs in the World to come? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Do their Souls then ſleep with their Bodies in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37517:13"/>Grave, or go to Purgatory? <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are we able to expreſs the Glory of that State, which God has prepared, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. and they enter into immediately after Death? <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shall they not enjoy a Beatifical viſion and enjoyment of God, with Saints and Angels, in the higheſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of Praiſe, without Sin or Suffering? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* and ſhall not their Bodies alſo partake of this Life of Glory at laſt? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.43.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS it not <hi>an everlaſting</hi> Life in oppoſition to this fading Life on Earth? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Will the Life above be Subject to decays, and changes, and interruptions in the happineſs of it? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Will they be in danger of forfeiting this happineſs, or any Enemy be admitted to diſpoſſeſs them of it? <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Is there not <hi>an everlaſting Death</hi> contrary to this everlaſting Life? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is this for the Wicked to have their beings taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and to remain no more? <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it not to be baniſhed from the preſence of God and to undergo the Torments of Hell for ever? 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Do we not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to teſtifie our firm Belief of theſe Articles? <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20, 21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doſt thou chiefly learn in theſe Articles of thy Belief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>I learn to believe in God the Father who hath made me, and all the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>in God the Son, who hath redeemed me, and all mankind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>in God the Holy Ghoſt, who ſanctifieth me, and all the Elect people of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS there not manifeſted a Divine order in the Works of the Bleſſed Trinity towards Men?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>When <hi>Creation</hi> is aſcribed to the Father, doth it mean that it was not the Work of the Son and Holy Ghoſt? <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it not that the Father did Create all things by the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37517:13"/>Son, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. and by the power of his Holy Spirit? <hi>Job</hi> 26.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And ſhould not <hi>we and all the World</hi> Worſhip and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the Lord our maker? <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the Work of <hi>Redemption</hi> peculiarly aſcribed to God the Son? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5, 6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Were we not by Sin bound over to the Wrath of God, and in ſlavery to Sin and Satan? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Could any meaner Price than <hi>his bloud</hi> ſatisfy Gods juſtice for our Redemption? 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Could any leſs power than <hi>of his Spirit</hi> reſcue our Souls from the bondage of the Devil? <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DO you mean by his redeeming <hi>all mankind</hi> that all Men have equal benefit in the Price that He laid down? <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Yet is not the Price ſufficient for <hi>all</hi> as being the bloud of Him, that was truly God? <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Have not <hi>all</hi> Men indifferently a reprieve granted them and many Temporal favours by means of Chriſt's Death? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it a ſmall matter that hereby there are offers of Pardon and Salvation to <hi>every Creature</hi> whereever the Goſpel comes? <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is He not indeed <hi>a ranſom for all,</hi> being for <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> into which two parts <hi>all mankind</hi> are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided? <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* And may not <hi>all mankind</hi> mean a great many out of every Nation and Language? <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Should they then live as others do, who are in eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner the <hi>redeemed</hi> of the Lord? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the work of <hi>Sanctification</hi> peculiarly aſcribed to the Holy Ghoſt. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are not all that are Baptized Sanctify'd, or ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part for a Holy uſe? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And is not our Office and Miniſtry, by which you were ſo dedicated, from the Holy Spirit? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11, 13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Dare you then forget your Baptiſmal Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. or tread under Foot the bloud of the Covenant by which you were <hi>Sanctify'd? Heb.</hi> 10.29.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is this dedication enough without an <hi>inward Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37517:14"/>by the gracious operation of the Holy Ghoſt, in the renewing and converting the Soul? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS there not a certain number known to the Lord, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. whom the Father hath <hi>choſen</hi> to Sanctification and Holyneſs? 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is there any way for us to know our <hi>Election,</hi> but by <hi>Sanctification</hi> and effectual calling? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4, 5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You ſaid that your Bodfathers and Godmothers did promiſe for you, that you ſhould keep God's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments. Tell me how many they be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which be they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame which God ſpake in the Twentieth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Exodus, ſaying, I am the Lord thy God which brought thee out of the Land of Egypt, out of the Houſe of Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Thou ſhalt have none other Gods, but me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Image, nor the likeneſs of any thing that is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven above, or in the Earth beneath, or in the mater un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Earth. Thou ſhalt not bow down to them, nor Worſhip them. For I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, and viſit the Sins of the Fathers upon the Children, unto the third and fourth Generation of them that hate me, and ſhew mercy unto Thouſands in them that love me and keep my Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain: for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his name in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>Remember that thou keep Holy the Sabbath day. Sir days ſhalt thou labour, and do all that thou haſt to do: out the Seventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God. In it thou ſhalt do no manner of work, Thou, and thy Son, and thy Daughter, thy Man-ſervant, and thy Maid-ſervant, thy Cattle, and the Stranger that is within thy ſtates. For in Six days the Lord made Heaven and Earth, the Sea and all that in them is, and reſted the Seventh day; wherefore the Lord
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37517:14"/>bleſſed the</hi> (<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> Sabbath.</note>) <hi>Seventh day, and hallowed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother, that thy days may be long in the Land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>Thou ſhalt do no Murther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">VII. <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">VIII. <hi>Thou ſhalt not Steal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs againſt thy Neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">X. <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy Neighbours Houſe, thou ſhalt not covet thy Neighbours Wife, nor his Servant, nor his Maid, nor his Oxe, nor his Aſs, nor any thing that is his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the Moral Law (as diſtinct from the Judicial and Ceremonial Law) ſum'd up in theſe Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments? <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Were they not ſpoken by the voice of God with much Terrour and Majeſty on Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and written on two Tables of Stone? <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.4, 22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE not Unbelievers under the Curſe of the Law? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And when Believers are delivered from the Curſe, is the Law made void and of none effect to them? <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Have they not by the Law, the knowledge of Sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. and are they not driven thereby to Chriſt? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Do they not delight in the Law and take it as a bleſſed Rule for them to walk by? <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gan He be a true Believer that doth not acknowledge all the Commandments to be Holy, juſt and good? <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not the Commandments Spiritual, reaching the Heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. and forbidding all degrees of Sin with the occaſions of them? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.96.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Do you think it enough then, that you have learnt theſe words, without being taught the meaning of them?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Preface to theſe Commandments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>I am the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:37517:15"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS it not ſufficient Reaſon to keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that He is the Soveraign <hi>Lord,</hi> Author of our beings, and diſpoſer of our Lives? <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24, 28. <hi>Levit.</hi> 22.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not his ſpecial relation to his people, as <hi>their God</hi> in Covenant, a further Reaſon of Obedience? <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> excluded from the Covenant Intereſt in Him, that the <hi>Jews</hi> had of old? <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.29.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DID not God wonderfully by the hand of <hi>Moſes redeem</hi> the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egyptian bondage?</hi> Exod. 12.41.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* And is it a leſs Mercy to be <hi>delivered</hi> from the <hi>bondage</hi> of Antichriſt (miſtically called <hi>Egypt? Rev.</hi> 11.8).</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not God's <hi>redeeming</hi> us from the <hi>Spiritual bondage</hi> of Sin and Satan, a further Obligation upon us to obey him? <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74, 75.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Firſt Commandment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods</hi> ‖ <hi>but me.</hi> ‖ Heb. <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not this forbid the denying of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, or any of his Divine attributes? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. and 10.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth it not forbid having many Gods, or any other ſave the Lord? <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 5, 6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May we uſe Divination, or conſult with thoſe that do? <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.10, 11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we worſhip any Creature together with the true God? <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>N.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is the invocation of Saints and Angels then to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in the Church? <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth it not forbid all falſe opinions of God, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in denying the Trinity or perſons of the Son and Spirit? <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21, 22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we truſt in, love or fear any Creature more than God? <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do not men thus make riches, pleaſures and relations their God; yea, by Pride and vain Glory make Gods of themſelves? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 12.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:37517:15"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth it not condemn all neglect of God and his worſhip when men live as without God in the world? <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not all that men do againſt this Commandment done <hi>before</hi> him: and doth He mark and deteſt the Sin of Idolatry? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.20, 21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS it enough to have <hi>no other Gods</hi> if we alſo do not know and own the true God? 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not avouch the Lord to be our God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.17, 18. and Worſhip Him with a Spiritual Worſhip, Suited his nature? <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we Worſhip him aright without fear and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, humility and ſelf-abaſement? <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Job</hi> 42.5, 6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can it be done, without Faith in God through Chriſt, thankfulneſs, love and delight? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Will God accept of outward acts of Worſhip, without a Spiritual Principle and Spiritual ends and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns? <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Second Commandment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make unto thy Self any Graven Image,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. BESIDES the Spiritual Worſhip, is there not alſo outward Worſhip in kneeling and bowing down the Body? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May we pay this outward worſhip to Images of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever kind? <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it not impoſſible as well as unlawful, to make an Image of God, of the Trinity, or of any of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine perſons? <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.15, 16. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it unlawful to make an Image of Creatures for Civil and Hiſtorical uſes? <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.20, 21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* But is it not the higheſt affront to the Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to compare Him to Creatures? <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21 —26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we bring any ſuch Image into the Church, as an Object or means of Worſhip? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.4, 5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we worſhip God <hi>by</hi> Images, as ſuppoſing ſome Divine vertue to be lodg'd in them? <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.4, 5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we pretend to worſhip God in our <hi>Hearts,</hi> and bow down to an Image with our <hi>Bodyes? Dan.</hi> 3.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37517:16"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we be preſent at Image worſhip, without danger of Sin, and ſcandal? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> guilty of Idolatry in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping Images, and of Sacriledge in leaving out the Second Commandment?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we worſhip God in a way of our own or other Mens deviſing? <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.2, 8, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet hath not God allowed the Governours of his Church to order the external Circumſtances of his Worſhip, ſo that nothing be contrary to his own word? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4, 5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And may not ſuch Circumſtances (though not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly Commanded by God) come under the general Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of decency, edification, concord, and obedience to Magiſtrates? <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But may any Men under whatever pretence add to, alter, or take away from the Subſtance of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we have Carnal thoughts of God or groſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of him in our minds? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.3, 4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IF we muſt not worſhip him by Images; muſt not we do it in his own way, according to his word? <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Hath He not appointed his Goſpel Ordinances of Prayer, reading, hearing, Singing, and the uſe of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it enough to obſerve the matter of Ordinances without the Inſtituted manner or Order? 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May we then caſt off any of his Ordinances or account them unprofitable and vain? <hi>Mala.</hi> 3.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not his being <hi>the Lord our God</hi> the Lawgiver of his Church the reaſon of obedience to his Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not his <hi>Zeal</hi> for his Glory, a further reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all falſe Worſhip, or neglect of the true? <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth He not mark how we worſhip, and ſeverely puniſh them that break this Commandment? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.38.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And though they pretend love, doth not God account of Idolaters as of <hi>Haters</hi> of him, becauſe they hate his People and ways? 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:37517:16"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IF the Children of ſuch wicked Men prove Godly, ſhall they dye for their Fathers Sins? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.14, 17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But is it unjuſt with God, when the Children follow their Fathers Steps, to perſue them with Judgments for their Sins through divers Generations? <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 18.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not his <hi>Mercy</hi> far exceed his ſeverity when extended to thoſe that Worſhip him aright? <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.29.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Third Commandment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the name of God, that by which He is made known, as his Titles, attributes, ordinances and word?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth not this forbid the blaſpheming Gods <hi>name,</hi> and all curſing our Selves or others? <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.11, 14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we uſe any of the Titles of God or Chriſt careleſly or in our Common Diſcourſe? <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not all falſe Swearing or Perjury a tremendous prophanation of Gods <hi>name? Levit.</hi> 19.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we violate our Lawful Oaths; though made to our dammage, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4. or break our Faith, though ſworn to Infidels and Heriticks? <hi>Joſh.</hi> 9.18, 19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not raſh, paſſionate, and vain Swearing the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral abuſe of Gods <hi>name</hi> at this day? <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May we uſe Phariſaical Oaths, by Creatures, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34-36. or Popiſh Oaths, by <hi>Mary,</hi> the Maſs, &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May we uſe unneceſſary aſſeverations or ridiculous Oaths, in new Coyn'd words? <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.37.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are we not forbidden to abuſe his Grace and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. or by any unworthy carriage to expoſe his <hi>name</hi> to reproach? <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.9, 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we uſe any Scripture, Matter or Phraſe for jeſting and Sport? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we uſe vain repetitions, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.7. or call on his <hi>name</hi> for an Hypocritical pretence? <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.47.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:37517:17"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not all careleſs Lip-worſhip without the Heart a Prophaning the <hi>name</hi> of God? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DO not the prophaners of Gods <hi>name</hi> ſometimes eſcape the Judgment of men? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* But if God <hi>hold them guilty,</hi> and take the matter into his hand, can they then eſcape? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are they not ſometimes plagu'd in this World by the Curſe of God, <hi>Zech.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.58, 59. and is not a more dreadful Judgment reſerved for them in the other? <hi>Mala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 3.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS all Swearing, or taking an Oath, forbidden by this Commandment? <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not right Swearing a part of Goſpel Worſhip, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.23. and muſt we not do it (when called) in Truth, Judgment and Righteouſneſs? <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not Reverence <hi>his name</hi> in his Worſhip, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.9. call upon <hi>his name</hi> and bleſs it? <hi>Job</hi> 1.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not Honour <hi>his name</hi> in our Actions, and take heed that we deny it not before men? <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Fourth Commandment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Remember that thou keep Holy the Sabbath day,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. SEEING nature teacheth us there muſt be a time fixt for Gods worſhip, is it fit that it ſhould be left to men to determine it?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hath not God fix't a <hi>Seventh</hi> part of time, and made the obſerving it part of his Moral Law that ſhall not paſs away? <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was not the <hi>Sabbath</hi> ordain'd in Paradice, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.2, 3. obſerv'd before the Ceremonial Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.25. and ordered to continue in Goſpel times? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* But is it neceſſary to obſerve the <hi>ſame day</hi> of the Week, which the <hi>Jews</hi> obſerved before the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt? <hi>Mark.</hi> 2.28. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not the <hi>firſt day</hi> of the week on which He aroſe called the <hi>Lords day,</hi> Rev. 1.10. and mention'd as the known time for Worſhip in the Churches? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And have we not the conſtant Practice of the Church for this change, from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time to this day? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1. and 20.6, 7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:37517:17"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE we leſs oblig'd to Goſpel Ordinances on the <hi>Lords day</hi> than the <hi>Jews</hi> were to their le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal obſervances on their <hi>Sabbath? Levit.</hi> 23.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Should we not <hi>remember</hi> the Holy Sabbath to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for it before it comes? <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.54. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are we not to obſerve on the Sabbath a <hi>Reſt</hi> from all manner of common work and buſineſs? <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But muſt we neglect works of Piety (though done with bodily labour,) <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.5. or works of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and mercy? <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May we think and talk of the worldly buſineſs that we abſtain from doing, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31, 32, or run to Recreations and Secular Pleaſures? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt it not be a <hi>Holy</hi> Reſt, taken up in obſerving all duties of Divine Worſhip? <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not riſe Early, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.2. and perſiſt in the duties of the day without wearineſs or grudging? <hi>Amos.</hi> 8.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we keep a Sabbath aright if we wilfully neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or forſake the Publick Aſſemblies? <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet when they are over, is not the reſt of the day to be ſpent in repetition of what we have heard, Holy conference, and meditation? <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.14, 17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MAY Maſters of Families (into whoſe hands this Commandment is put, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.10.) ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any under their charge to Prophane the Sabbath?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And muſt not Magiſtrates enjoyn the obſervation of the Sabbath, and puniſh the neglect? <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.17, 22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet if they neglect it, will God ſuffer Sabbath break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to go unpuniſht? <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† And are days of Faſting and Thankſgiving, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully appointed, to be Religiouſly obſerv'd? <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.16. and 9.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DARE you rob God of what He claims an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in, when He hath allowed you Six days for your own Work?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hath not God given his own Example by reſting Himſelf on the Seventh day, and bleſſing and hallowing the Sabbath? <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Doth not the keeping the Sabbath tend highly to the Honour or God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. and the preſerving
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37517:18"/>his Worſhip in the World? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can we expect a bleſſing on our Week-days Labour, if we prophane the Sabbath? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet is it enough to Worſhip God on the Lords day, if we neglect his Worſhip on other days? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Fifth Commandment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not this Commandment enjoyn the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual duties of Superiours and Inferiours to each other in every Relation?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(1.) Muſt not <hi>Children</hi> honour their natural <hi>Parents,</hi> the Authors of their being under God? <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* If Parents are Aged, Poor or Weak, may Children deſpiſe them, in Heart or Carriage? <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt they not fear to offend them, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.3. and Submit to their reproofs and corrections? <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt they not obey their Commands in all Lawful things, though they ſeem harſh and ſevere? <hi>Col.</hi> 3.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May they murmur at their Proviſion or reject their advice in Marriage or matters of moment? <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.21. and 26.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt they not follow their Godly Inſtructions and examples, <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.1, 3. and endeavour to be a Comfort to them in their old Age? <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.1. and 25.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May they divulge their infirmities, waſt their eſtates, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.26. or reflect diſhonour upon them by their wicked Lives? <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt they not endeavour to requite their Parent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in praying for them, and maintaining them if they be in want? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And muſt not Children by Adoption and affinity ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their Parents? <hi>Eſth.</hi> 2.7, 20. <hi>Ruth.</hi> 3.1, 5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DO not Parents owe to their Children tender, ſincere and conſtant Love? <hi>Col.</hi> 3.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May they under pretence of loving them, loſe their juſt Authority over them?. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Having ſeriouſly devoted them to God, muſt they not diligently teach and inſtruct them? <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6-8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May they ſuffer them to live in idleneſs, without a Lawful Calling and honeſt labour? <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt they not mark their Inclinations and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37517:18"/>reprove them for their faults, and (in caſe of ſin and ſtubbornneſs) correct them? <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.15, 17. and 23.13, 14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But may they by reproachful Language and wicked Commands, provoke them to wrath and diſcourage them? <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* <hi>Muſt</hi> they not ſet them a good example, and dayly pray for a bleſſing upon them? <hi>Job</hi> 1.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(2.) Muſt not Servants <hi>honour</hi> their Maſters, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1. and obey their juſt Commands? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May they by ſtubborn ſilence, private mutterings, or croſs anſwers, provoke their Maſters? <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May they waſt their Maſters Goods, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.9. or neglect his buſineſs, when his Eye is off? <hi>Col.</hi> 3.22, 23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt they not bleſs God for Godly Maſters, pray for them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.12. and ſubmit to Inſtructions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. SHOULD Maſters, that would mind their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be indifferent or careleſs about what Servants they take into their Houſes? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.6, 7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May they rule over them with rigour, as if they were Slaves or Beaſts, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.46. without regard to the health of their Bodies, <hi>Mat</hi> 8.5, 6. or good of their Souls? <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt they not give them what is juſt and equal, as to Inſtruction, Proviſion, Work and Wages? <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.15. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(3.) Is not the duty of Wives Sum'd up in a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and quiet Subjection, and the duty of Husbands in an entire and intenſe love? <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.24, 25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(4.) Are not Magiſtrates our civil <hi>Parents, Iſa.</hi> 49.23. and muſt we not <hi>Honour</hi> and Reverence them? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we revile our Rulers, or uſe any indecent words concerning them? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Acts</hi> 23.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not by all juſt means defend their perſons, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2. pay them Taxes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.21. and be Subject to their lawful Commands? <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MAY Magiſtrates forget by whom they Reign, or caſt off the fear of God in their Covern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:37517:19"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(5.) Are not Miniſters our Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Parents,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.12. whom we muſt know, <hi>Honour</hi> and eſteem? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12, 13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we defraud them of their maintenance, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11. or deſpiſe their Godly Diſciplines? <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not receive their Holy Doctrines as the word of God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. and conſult with them in difficult Caſes? <hi>Mala.</hi> 2.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MUST Not Miniſters be Holy in their Carriage, apt to teach, able to convince gain-ſayers and to Comfort the afflicted? <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(6.) May we neglect a ſuitable reſpect and Honour to any others that are above us, in Age, Gifts, or quality? <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.32.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not this the firſt Commandment with Promiſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.2, 3. becauſe Obedience thereunto tends to proſperity and the lengthening out of our days? <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Doth not this ſhew us that Honouring our Parents is well-pleaſing to God, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.20. and that Godlineſs hath the promiſes of this Life as well as that to come? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But if Children are Hypocritically Obedient, hath He Promiſed not to cut them off for their other ſins?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yea if Children be Godly and Dutiful for Chriſt's ſake, is this Promiſe abſolute without any Condition? 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 14.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May He not take them away from the evils of this <hi>Life,</hi> and give them the bleſſing of eternal <hi>Life? Iſa.</hi> 57.1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Can they that perſiſt in diſobedience to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents eſcape the dreadful Curſe pronounc'd on the breakers of this Commandment? <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.16. <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Sixth Commandment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Thou ſhalt not Kill.</hi> Or, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no Murder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not this forbid the taking away unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the life of Man, who was made after the Image of God? <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.3, 6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37517:19"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it Murder or unlawful for the Magiſtrate to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the lives of Criminals by Publick Juſtice? <hi>Num.</hi> 35.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it Murder to ſhed Bloud in a Lawful War, <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.10. or to kill a Man in our neceſſary ſelf-defence? <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.2, 3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it not Murder to kill a Man in a Paſſion, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.23. and yet greater if done with malice and fixed hatred? <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not the ſin yet greater if done by force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in an open aſſault, <hi>Num.</hi> 35.16. or by Witchcraft and help of the Devil? <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth blind Zeal excuſe the Murderer, if He ſhould think He ought to do it? <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are Duels Lawful, or can any pretence of Gallantry, or injuries receiv'd, excuſe them? <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth it not forbid all hurting and wounding our Neighbours Bodies, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.24, 25. and all occaſions of Bloud-ſhed? <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we by Contrivance, hiring, or falſe Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſent or be acceſſary to Murder? <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.10-12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not Self-murder a moſt unnatural Sin and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out poſſibility of Repentance? <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth not all Murder make Men odious to God, and like the Devil, who was a Murderer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning? <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are not all rayling and reviling Words, and all malice and unjuſt anger in the Heart, as murder in Gods account? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.21, 22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS it ſufficient that we do not ſtrike or wound our Neighbour, if we uſe no due care to preſerve his Life? <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.33.—36.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not ſuccour the diſtreſſed, protect the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and deliver them from wrongs? <hi>Job</hi> 29.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we needleſly hazard our own lives, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.23. or neglect the moderate uſe of Food, Phyſick, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or what may tend to the Health of our Bodies? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Seventh Commandment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Thou ſhalt not Commit Adultery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:37517:20"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MAY any forbid Marriage which God has ordain'd for mutual Society, the avoiding Fornication, and the increaſe of the Church? <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it Lawful for any to have more Wives than one, <hi>Mala.</hi> 2.15. or to put away his Wife, ſaving for the cauſe of Fornication? <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it Lawful to contract Marriage with thoſe that are near of Kin within the degrees mentioned in the Law? <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it not a ſhame to mention the ſecret Luſts of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs whereby ſinners defile their own and others bodies, in a ſingle or married State? <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not <hi>Adultery</hi> or the breach of the marriage Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Mala.</hi> 2.14. the direct ſin againſt this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t doth it excuſe the uncleanneſs, called Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that it is committed by ſingle perſons, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 18. or with a purpoſe and promiſe of marriage after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards? <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do not theſe ſins bring deſtruction on Nations and Families, and ruin on the Eſtate and reputation of the ſinner? <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.26, 33.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do they not deſtroy the health and lives, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.8, 11, and more eſpecially the Souls of the guilty? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are they uſually committed by any but who are firſt given up by God and abhorred by him? <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are there many Inſtances of thoſe that have return'd and repented after the commiting of ſuch ſins? <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.18, 19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do they not expoſe men to Excommunication from the Church and to Damnation in Hell? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. and 6.9, 10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth not this Law extend to the forbidding the Luſtings of the Heart, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28. the uncleanneſs of the Tongue, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.29. and the adultery of the Eye? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May we read wanton Books, wear immodeſt Attire, <hi>Prov</hi> 7.10. live in idleneſs, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2. or have fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar converſe with unchaſt perſons? <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not Gluttony and Drunkenneſs the great incentives to the Luſts of uncleanneſs? <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.31-33.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:37517:20"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MUST we not take great care to preſerve our own and others Chaſtity, in heart, ſpeech, and behaviour? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can this be done without watching over our Senſes, <hi>Job</hi> 31.1. and watching againſt Temptations, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. eſpecially in a time of Youth? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Eighth Commandment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Thou ſhalt not Steal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. HATH God left all things in Common for every one that is ſtrongeſt or moſt crafty to ſeize on what He can get? <hi>Habak.</hi> 2.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it not theft to take away anothers Goods unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.6. though never ſo ſecretly? <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we be Confederates with Thieves, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.10.—14, pertake of, or receive what they have Stollen, or conceal their Perſons or Goods? <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it not aggravated by the violence that is uſed in Robbery and Piracy, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.25. or by Stealing things Dedicated to God, called Sacriledge? <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May men waſt Riotouſly their own Eſtates, and thereby Rob themſelves and their Families? <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not Theft contrary to the Light of Nature as well as the Law of Chriſt, and doth it not expoſe the Guilty to a ſevere Condemnation? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we uſe any unlawful calling, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. or any Guile or defrauding, though in a lawful calling? <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.19. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we put off bad or falſe Wares and Mony for good, or uſe Falſe Weights and Meaſures? <hi>Amos.</hi> 8.5, 6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we ſet unconſcionable Prices on our Goods, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.14, 16. or Work upon the ignorance or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of them we deal with? <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.22, 23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we buy of thoſe that we vehemently ſuſpect have no right to Sell, or immoderately praiſe our own, or diſpraiſe anothers Goods? <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it not grievous Theft to be falſe in Places or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Truſt, eſpecially in the Wills of the Dead? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we refuſe to pay juſt Debts, if we are able, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8. or borrow without being likely to pay,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37517:21"/>unleſs we lay open our Caſe? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we treſpaſs upon the Lands of others, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.28. or with-hold corn to advance the Price in a time of ſcarcity? <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we keep Loſt Goods which we have found, without a ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>table diligence to enquire out the Owner? <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.2, 3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MUST we then in a Lawful uſe of ſome good C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lling caſt our care upon the Lord and eat our own bread? <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.28. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.11, 12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not do to others as we would be done by, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. Give to all their due, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. and Linder what we can any damage from befalling our Neighbours Eſtate? <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can there be true Repentance for ſins of injuſtice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſtoring what we have defrauded, to the utmoſt of our power? <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.10, 11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not give largely of our well-gotten Goods to the Poor, according to their neceſſity, eſpecially to the Godly and them that ſuffer for Chriſts ſake? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Ninth Commandment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe Witneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not this in the Letter forbid the affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing falſely againſt another in Courts of Judicature? <hi>Acts</hi> 6.11, 13. and 24.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we therefore for fear, favour, or malice, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the truth, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.19, 20. or knowingly change or wreſt the words of another? <hi>Mar.</hi> 26.60, 61.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we ſuborn falſe Witneſſes, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.9, 10. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> may Judges and Juries Wittingly admit of them, to Juſtify the Wicked or condemn the Righteous? <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* And though it be in common converſe, may we raiſe falſe Reports, <hi>Neh.</hi> 6.6, 8. or lightly take them up and ſpread them? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we put the worſt Conſtructions on our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours words and actions, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.9, 10. or carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Tales openly or ſecretly to diſgrace him? <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not all falſe Witneſſing and Slandering injurious to Men and hateful to God? <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.19, 20. and 19.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:37517:21"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth not this Condemn all <hi>Lying,</hi> as highly provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, contrary to all Society amongſt men, and making men like the Devil the Father of it? <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.16, 17. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it Lawful to <hi>Lye,</hi> under pretence of Gods Glory, the preſervation of Religion, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.7, 8. or for any Worldly gain whatſoever? <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And if we may not Lye for our own or others Profit, may we for their Sport or Pleaſure? <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.18, 19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May we uſe Artificial modes of Lying, by Equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Mental Reſervations? <hi>Acts</hi> 5.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet the more pernicious and hurtful any Lye is to our Neighbour, is it not ſo much the more abominable? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MUST not all behave themſelves in Courts of Judicature, as under the awe of the peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar preſence and Oath of God? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not in our whole Converſation Love the Truth, and (when we are called to ſpeak) utter it? <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May we Promiſe any thing that we intend not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, or neglect the performance, if it be Lawful?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not rejoyce in the <hi>good Name</hi> of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and be grieved when they deſerve or receive diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not Charitably think the beſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. and cover th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ir Faults, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8. and in what we can ſpeak well of them? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.4, 5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet muſt we neglect to reprove them for their Faults, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.17. till they prove ſcorners or deſperate? <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we rightly take care of our Neighbours <hi>good Name</hi> if we do not by a Holy walking, endeavour to preſerve our own? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Tenth Commandment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Thou ſhalt not Covet thy Neighbours Houſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE we forbidden not only the acts and ſetled thoughts of ſin, but even the firſt motions and ſtirrings thereof in our Souls? <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we comply with the Devils moti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 5.3. or ſuffer our ſelves to be drawn aſide by o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:37517:22"/>to affect any thing forbidden by God's Law? <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we deſire what is anothers to his hurt, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.33. or envy our Neighbours happineſs, and delight in his loſs? <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.17, 18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Though we Covet not anothers Goods, may we ſet our affections on our own, or diſtract our mind and waſt our ſtrength in perſuit of the World? <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.15, 17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth not Covetouſneſs bring a Curſe on the Goods, Bodies, Families, and Souls of Worldlings? <hi>Habak.</hi> 2.9, 10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not this require all inward purity of the Soul, and the regulating our affections by the Word? <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not rejoyce in our Neighbours proſperity <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.12. and be contented with what Condition the providence of God allots us? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.6, 8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doſt thou chiefly learn by theſe Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I learn two things: my duty towards God and my duty towards my Neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. WAS not the Law Written on two Tables, the one containing our Duty to God, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our duty to men, and both Comprehended in Love? <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.1-5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can thoſe two be ſeparated in our Practice and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or is our <hi>Holineſs</hi> true without <hi>righteouſneſs? Luk.</hi> 1.75.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet are not the duties of the firſt Table more noble than the duties of the Second, as the Object of them, which is <hi>God,</hi> is greater than <hi>Man? Job</hi> 33.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is thy duty towards God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My duty towards God is to believe in him, to fear him, and to love him, with all my Heart, with all my
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37517:22"/>mind, with all my Soul, and with all my Strength: To Worſhip him to give him thanks, to put my whole truſt in him, to call upon him, to Honour his Holy Name and his word, and to ſerve him truly all the days of my Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not the Four firſt Commandments make up the firſt Table, and is not Love to God the Sum of them all? <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37, 38.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can we Love God aright, if we Love him not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and this with a Superlative Love? <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can Faith be true that works not by Love, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. or that Love real that ſhows not it Self in keeping his Commandments? <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.10, 14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And doth not Love to God make our obedience more willing, chearful, active and abiding? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Seeing we cannot Love God without meaſure (as He is good without meaſure) ought we to Love him leſs, then with all our Heart, mind, might and Strength? <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is thy duty towards thy Neighbour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My duty towards my Neighbour is to love him as my Self, and to do to all men, as I mould they ſhould do unto me; To love, honour, and ſuccour my Father and Mother. To honour, and obey the King, and all that are put in Authority under Him. To ſubmit my Self to all my Governours, Teachers, Spirital Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Maſters. To order my Self lowly, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendly to all my Betters. To hurt no body by Word or Deed. To be true and juſt in all my Dealing. To bear no malice nor hatred in my Heart. To keep my Hands from picking and ſtealing, and my Tongue from evil ſpeaking, lying and ſtandering. To keep my Body in temperance, ſoberneſs and charity, not to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet, nor deſire other Mens Goods, but to learn and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour truly to get mine own living, and to do my duty, in that State of Life unto which it ſhall pleaſe God to call me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not the Second Table contain the Six Laſt Commandments, and is not Love to our Neighbour the Sum of them all? <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.39.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not all thoſe meant by our <hi>Neighbours,</hi> with whom
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37517:23"/>we have any Dealings or converſe? <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.29-36.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not love our Neighbours, with a pure, hearty, and unfeigned love, as we love our ſelves? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet muſt we love all <hi>equally,</hi> with the ſame meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> kind of love?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> is not natural <hi>affection</hi> due to Relations, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> love of <hi>Reverence</hi> to Superiours, and of <hi>complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> delight, to the Godly? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* But muſt we deny a love of <hi>Compaſſion</hi> to all in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and a love of <hi>Benevolence</hi> to our very Enemies? <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.32, 33.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† And can we do our duty required in theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>dments without this Grace of <hi>love</hi> and Charity? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1-7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. NOW you have heard theſe Commandments explained, do you think that you are able per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to fulfil the Law of God? <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.20. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt you not lament your ſinfulneſs and weakneſs, and depend on Chriſt for Righteouſneſs and Strength? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And do you not ſtand to your promiſe, that in deſire and conſtant endeavour you will Practice ſincere obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God's Commandments? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6, 48.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Catechiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My good Child, know this that thou art not able to do theſe things of thy Self, nor to walk in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, and to ſerve him, without his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Grace, which thou muſt learn at all times to call for by diligent Prayer</hi>—</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not Prayer a neceſſary part of Worſhip in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the obtaining Grace, <hi>Rom</hi> 10 13. and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing much, when perform'd aright<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 5 16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is there any other object of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> Prayer, but <hi>God,</hi> who alone ſearcheth the Hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 6.30.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is Prayer a bare ſpeaking the words with our <hi>Mouths,</hi> without the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ng out the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es of our <hi>Hearts? Pſal.</hi> 25.1. and 42.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we omit any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the kinds of Prayer, Publick in the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42 private in the Family, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.25. and ſecret in the Cloſet? <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37517:23"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not often lift up our Hearts in Holy Ejacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.164. and ſometimes uſe extraordinary Prayer with Faſting? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not know the matter of our Prayers by our wants, but chiefly by the Precepts and Promiſes of God? <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Have we any other Mediatour, whoſe name we can come in, ſave our Lord Jeſus Chriſt? <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.13, 14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we perform this duty aright without the Holy Spirit, to help our infirmities, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. and to ſtir up Holy affections and Graces in the Soul? <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Muſt we joyn with our deſires the Graces of Faith, Humility and Self-denyal; and are you deſirous ſo to Pray?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>—<hi>Let me hear therefore if thou canſt ſay the Lords Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven; Hallowed by thy name. Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven. Give us this day our day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread. And forgive us our treſpaſſes, As we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given them that treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For thine is the Kingdom, and the power and the Glory, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not this call'd the Lords Prayer, becauſe the Lord himſelf Compoſed it, and taught it his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we refuſe to uſe theſe words as a <hi>Form,</hi> ſo excellent for the Author, matter and method, and as being part of Chriſt's own word and Preſcription? <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet ſeeing it is ſo general and Comprehenſive, Is it unlawful to uſe other words in Prayer?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not this then a perfect <hi>Pattern</hi> of Prayer to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us in the matter and manner of our Supplications? <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Preface of the Lords Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:37517:24"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. CAN there be a greater encouragement to come to God in Prayer, than this, that He is the <hi>Father</hi> of Believers by adoption? <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it not a fearful thing to come before God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Special Intereſt in him? <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.29.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can we have acceſs to him any way but by Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.14. or have an evidence of our Intereſt, but by the Spirit of adoption? <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth not this Relation require dutiful affections, ſuch as filial fear, love and confidence when we draw near Him? <hi>Mala.</hi> 1.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MUST not they who ſay <hi>Our</hi> Father, live as the Children of one Father, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.8. and Pray for and with one another? <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.36.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the God to whom we Pray (though pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent every where, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7, 8.) moſt gloriouſly preſent in the higheſt <hi>Heavens? Iſa.</hi> 63.15. and 66.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is there any thing which a God <hi>in Heaven</hi> cannot give, if it be good for us? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Should not poor crawling worms come with a great awe and reverence before the God of <hi>Heaven? Eccl.</hi> 5.1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it fit to have <hi>Earthly</hi> Hearts, when we Worſhip a <hi>Heavenly</hi> Father? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123.1. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.41.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not the God of <hi>Heaven</hi> equally near to all his Petitioners in whatſoever parts of the <hi>Earth? Acts</hi> 17.27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Firſt Petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Hallowed be thy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the <hi>Hallowing</hi> Gods Name, to Honour and Glorify Him in all things by which He makes himſelf known?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can the <hi>Name</hi> of God be ever impure <hi>in it Self,</hi> or otherwiſe than Holy and glorious? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.1, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet is not his <hi>Name</hi> diſhonoured by ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23. and reproach'd and blaſphem'd by Sinners? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:37517:24"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not beg Grace, to <hi>Hallow his Name</hi> in our <hi>Hearts;</hi> by acknowledging and honouring it, as Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely Holy? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can we thus <hi>Sanctify</hi> his Name, unleſs he firſt <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy</hi> our Hearts and make them Holy? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not deſire Grace, to <hi>Honour</hi> him with our <hi>mouths, Joſh.</hi> 7 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.30. and in our <hi>lives,</hi> by worſhipping and obeying Him? <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we <hi>honour his name</hi> aright, without deſiring that others alſo might Glorifie and <hi>hallow his name? Pſal.</hi> 145.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not beg that He would <hi>glorifie his own name</hi> in the World, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67.1, 2, 3. and pull down what is Contrary to his Glory therein? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.16. &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Second Petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Thy Kingdom come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. HATH not God a general <hi>Kingdom</hi> over all, and muſt we not deſire that His Soveraign Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may be every where acknowledged? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.19. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.32.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it enough to be under his <hi>Providential</hi> Dominion (as are all creatures) unleſs we be made the Subjects of his <hi>Kingdom of Grace?</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Do you not beg then to be delivered from the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Satan, under which you were by Nature, that Chriſt may Reign in you by his Grace and Spirit? <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And that He would make you fit for, and give you an abundant entrance into the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Heaven? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are you to neglect others in your Prayers, ſo as not to deſire the ſpreading of the word of his <hi>Kingdom?</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it not highly deſirable that the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of the world ſhould be all the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of Chriſt; and <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> given him for his poſſeſſion? <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can we pray for this, without deſiring the pulling down of Antichriſt and all the implacable enemies of the Church? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not deſire the haſtning of his <hi>Kingdom of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37517:25"/>Glory</hi> in which all the Saints ſhall have with him their perfect Conſummation and bliſs? <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Third Petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Thy will be done in Earth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS it fit for us curiouſly to enquire into the <hi>ſecret will</hi> of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.7. or can we know it, but by the event and courſe of his Providence? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not deſire that we may ſubmit to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential Will when diſcovered (according to our Lords Pattern, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.42.) without murmuring or repining? <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13, 14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* But muſt we not deſire to know his <hi>revealed will, Acts</hi> 9.6. and renounce our own Wills ſo far as they ſtand in Competition with his? <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.30.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it ſufficient to know his Will, without deſiring that He would enable us to perform it? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. CAN we do the Will of God here on Earth with that perfection that Saints and Angels do above? <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.8, 9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>But muſt we not aim at perfection, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13, 14. and deſire to do His Will as they do, <hi>ſpeedily, Iſa.</hi> 6.2. <hi>faithfully, Pſal.</hi> 103.20, 21. and <hi>conſtantly? Mat.</hi> 18.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Fourth Petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Give us this day our dayly Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DO we deſerve the leaſt crumb of Bread, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10. or can we procure it by our Induſtry and Labour without the gift of God? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.1, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>If all be of free gift, may we murmur that others have more than we, or that God takes away any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſſing from us? <hi>Job</hi> 1.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Yet muſt we not pray, for ſuch a Competency of <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> v. 2. <hi>Sleep</hi> and <hi>Safety, Pſal.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Raiment</hi> as He ſees fit? <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not deſire that He would give fruitful Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and a Bleſſing on the <hi>Fruits of the Earth?</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.35, 36.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:37517:25"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Muſt we ask theſe things chiefly or in the firſt place, before the Spiritual <hi>Bread</hi> for our Souls? <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May we when we have <hi>daily bread,</hi> long for Riches, delicacies and abundance? <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we live by this <hi>bread</hi> alone, without deſiring his <hi>word of bleſſing</hi> upon it? <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it <hi>our</hi> dayly Bread, or can we pray for a bleſſing on it, if it be the Bread of Idleneſs, violence or Injuſtice? 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not come <hi>day by day</hi> like Beggers for what we need, and depend on God for freſh ſupplies? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.27-29.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* And when we ask for Bread <hi>this day</hi> may we be anxiouſly careful about <hi>to morrow? Mat.</hi> 6.34.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† And when He beſtowes upon us our dayly Bread, muſt we not receive it with Thankſgiving? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4, 5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Fifth Petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Forgive us our Treſpaſſes,</hi> &amp;c. Gr. <hi>Debts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IF we have our daily Bread and never ſo much of the world, can we be happy without the Pardon of ſin? <hi>Job</hi> 21.7-15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not our ſins called <hi>Treſpaſſes</hi> and <hi>Debts</hi> as making us obnoxious to the puniſhment threatned? <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.32, 35.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not pray that God, for his mercy ſake through Chriſt, would not exact the penalty of us, but deliver us from the guilt of all our ſins? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.2, 3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not therefore beg repentance unto Life and Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, who bore the penalty? <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* May they, who have been pardon'd already, neglect to pray for the continuances of that Grace and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of their dayly Infirmities? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.11. and 51.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt they not pray for the manifeſtation of forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to their Souls, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 51.8. and to be openly abſolv'd at the great day? <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MAY any think or hope that God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given him, that doth not find in his Heart a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37517:26"/>readineſs to forgive others? <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.15. and 18.32, 34.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Though we may ſeek help peaceably of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, when we are injured, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.11. yet may we bear a grudge for injuries done, or privately revenge them? <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not profeſs our readineſs to forgive o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when we deſire God to forgive us? <hi>Mark.</hi> 11.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And muſt we not do it heartily, fully, and freely, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.21, 22, 35. as God for Chriſt's ſake forgives us? <hi>Col.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.32.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it not an encouragement to our Faith, that God upon our repentance will forgive <hi>us,</hi> when ſuch as we are enabled by his Grace to forgive <hi>others? Luk.</hi> 11.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the Sixth Petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>And lead us not into Temptation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS it enough to beg pardon for what is paſt, if we are not careful to be kept from ſin for the time to come? <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is temptation an excuſe for ſin, or doth God tempt any one by enticing them to iniquity? <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not men tempted by their own Luſts, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.14. and by the Devils ſtirring up the corruptions of their hearts? <hi>Acts</hi> 5.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not beg that (if God pleaſe) we may not fall into ſuch Circumſtances, where we ſhall meet with occaſions and provocations to ſin? <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.7-9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not pray, that if we are tempted, He would not leave us to our Selves, or withdraw his Grace? 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 32.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can we have wiſdom to know the Devils wiles, or ſtrength to withſtand them, without asking it of God? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7-9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not beg that if we fall by temptation we may riſe again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.12. and that God wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d at laſt free us from all temptation? <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MUST we not deſire to be <hi>delivered</hi> from this preſent <hi>evil</hi> world, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4 and all the real <hi>evil</hi> of afflictions? <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not pray to be <hi>delivered</hi> from <hi>evil</hi> men,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37517:26"/>2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2, 3. and that the Church may be freed from its oppreſſours? <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.7, 8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* But is there any greater <hi>evil</hi> than that of ſin, or any greater mercy to be beg'd, than to be <hi>delivered</hi> from the guilt and power of it? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Muſt we not deſire to be <hi>delivered</hi> from the <hi>evil</hi> one, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. and from the wrath of God in the world to come? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the Concluſion of the Lords Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>For thine is the Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MAY we take arguments in Prayer from our own merits, or from any thing but God, his Name and Grace? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.1. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not He that hath <hi>the Kingdom</hi> ready to ſave his Subjects; and He that hath <hi>the power</hi> able to do it, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when His <hi>Glory</hi> is alſo concern'd? 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 20.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not this a Form of Thankſgiving, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.11. and muſt not Honour and Glory and Power be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to Him, now and for ever? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. CAN we ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to Prayers which we do not underſtand or attend to? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15, 16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do we not by ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> teſtify our earneſt <hi>deſire</hi> of what we pray for, and <hi>truſt,</hi> through Chriſt that we ſhall obtain it? <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What deſireſt thou of God in this Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I deſire my Lord God our Heavenly Father, who is the giver of all goodneſs, to ſend his Grace unto me, and to all People, that we may Worſhip him, ſerve him, and obey him as we ought to do. And I pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, that He will ſend us all things that be needful both for our Souls and Bodies and that He will be merciful unto us and forgive us our Sins: and that it will pleaſe him to ſave and defend us in all dangers ghoſtly and Bodily; and that He will keep us from all Sin and wickedneſs, and from our Ghoſtly Enemy, and from everlaſting death. And this I truſt He will do of his mercy and goodneſs, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and therefore I ſay, Amen. So be it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:37517:27"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. CAN we aright <hi>Petition</hi> God for mercy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of our vileneſs and unworthineſs, and <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> for what we have received? <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we in <hi>Confeſſion</hi> reckon up all the ſins that ever we committed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12. and 40.12. or if we could, is it to inform God of what He knew not before? 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it not to unburden our loaded Conſciences before the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.4, 5. to acknowledge his juſtice and to lay hold on his mercy? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt it not be ſincere and full, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13. with grief and confuſion of Face? <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is there any Condition that a Believer can be in, in which <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> may not be joyn'd with his Prayer? <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not value his mercys for their number, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and freeneſs, declare them to others, and live ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thereunto? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12.—14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How many Sacraments hath Chriſt ordained in his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two only, as generally neceſſary to Salvation, that is to ſay, Baptiſm and the Supper of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§ IF we hope to obtain the mercy we pray for, may we neglect the other means of Grace; attending on his word, and uſe of his Sacraments? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41, 42.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are the two Sacraments of the old Teſtament, <hi>Cir cumciſion</hi> and the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> to be uſed in the Church now? <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hath not Chriſt appointed two other Sacraments in their room; anſwering to our neceſſity, of a <hi>new birth</hi> and of <hi>Spiritual growth?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and <hi>the Lords Supper,</hi> civil appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments uſed without the Church (as <hi>Marriage</hi> amongſt Heathens) or meer Ceremonies of indifferent and Arbitrary uſe? <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are they only <hi>ſpecially</hi> neceſſary to ſome one ſort of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37517:27"/>Believers (as <hi>Ordination</hi> is to Miniſters) to which others are not oblig'd?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are they ſo <hi>particularly</hi> neceſſary, to every perſon under all Circumſtances, that no one can be ſaved that doth not pertake of them? <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are they not then <hi>generally</hi> neceſſary, where they may be had, by vertue of Gods Command, that no one upon peril of his Soul, may wilfully contemn them? <hi>Num.</hi> 9.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What meaneſt thou by this word Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I mean an outward and viſible ſign of an inward Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Grace, given unto us ordain'd, by Chriſt himſelf, as a means whereby we receive the ſame, and a pledge to aſſure us thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> fignify our engagement to Chriſt, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Souldiers were to their Emperours by their military Oath?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(1) Can it be a Sacrament, where there is not ſome <hi>outward ſign</hi> ſenſible and viſible? <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not ſuch ſigns of great uſe, to inform our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, quicken our memories, and ſtir up our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(2.) Muſt there not be ſome <hi>inward and ſpiritual Grace</hi> that may anſwer to the outward ſign?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(3.) Yet can it be a Sacrament unleſs this Grace be <hi>given to us,</hi> viz. by offer and Promiſe made to us therein? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are the Benefits of Chriſt's death (though conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally) offer'd and promiſed in theſe rites?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(4.) Muſt not a Sacrament be <hi>Ordained by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. and hath not He, beſides his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Sanctify'd theſe by his own pertaking of them?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can any meer man ordain a Sacrament or annex Grace or any promiſe thereof to their own inventions?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(5.) Muſt not a Sacrament be a <hi>means to receive the Grace</hi> promiſed, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. and doth not God indeed conveigh Grace to the worthy receivers? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth the efficacy of the Sacraments depend upon the intention or<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> worthineſs of the Perſon that adminiſters them? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:37517:28"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do the Sacraments work of themſelves, by any Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral vertue in the outward rites? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are they not <hi>means</hi> of Grace made effectual by the working of the Spirit to them that by Faith do pertake of them? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(6.) Can there be any Sacrament, where there is not a Seat or <hi>pledge to aſſure</hi> this to us? <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do not Believers in the Sacraments Seal their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5. and receive the Benefits of the new Covenant Seal'd to them? <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How many parts are there in a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two. The outward viſible ſign and the inward Spiritual Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. ARE theſe the only parts of it; or doth a bare <hi>ſign</hi> of Grace, without a <hi>Promiſe</hi> and <hi>Inſtitution</hi> make a Sacrament? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do you not mention theſe two parts, for the better Explication of each particular Sacrament following?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the outward viſible ſign or Form in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Water, wherein the Perſon is Baptiſed in the name of the Father, of the Son and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not water the Element in which Baptiſm is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, and was not Chriſt and his Diſciples Baptized therein? <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36. and 10.44.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May any for the meaneſs of its outſide, or under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a higher Baptiſm, contemn this? 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can any thing be more apt, to ſignify the blood and Spirit of Chriſt, than <hi>water;</hi> for the neceſſity, freeneſs, ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ty, and the Cleanſing. Vertue thereof? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. DOTH not <hi>Baptizing</hi> ſignify, the application of water to a perſon or thing in greater or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37517:28"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſſer quantities? <hi>Mark.</hi> 7.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it probable that when Thouſands were Baptized in a day; and ſome Baptized in private houſes, and by night that they were all plung'd under water?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Doth not the <hi>Sprinkling</hi> with or <hi>pouring on</hi> of water aptly expreſs the bloud <hi>of ſprinkling, Heb.</hi> 10.22. and 12.24. and <hi>pouring</hi> out of the Spirit? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. CAN any adminiſter Baptiſm but they who are ſent and Commiſſioned, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.33. or may they do it in their own names, or the name of any Creature? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13, 15</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt it not be in the name of the Trinity, to ſhew by whoſe authority it is done, and who alone can make it effectual? <hi>Mat.</hi> 28 19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† And is not the perſon ſo Baptized engag'd to the Profeſſion and worſhip of Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the inward and Spiritual Grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A death unto Sin, and a new birth unto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for being by nature born in Sin, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath, we are hereby made the Children of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the <hi>new Birth</hi> or Regeneration (which is a Change of State and Heart) ſignify'd and Sealed in our Baptiſm? <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(1.) Are there any, that (before the <hi>relative change</hi> by Regeneration) are not <hi>by nature Children of Wrath? <hi>Eph.</hi>
                        </hi> 2.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not <hi>Juſtification</hi> ſignify'd by Baptiſm, whereby our Souls are ſprinkled with Chriſts blood, as our bodies are with water? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.28. and 22.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And are not they who are thus juſtified, accepted as <hi>the Children of Grace</hi> by adoption.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(2.) Can any have this Relative change, without a <hi>real change</hi> of Heart and life accompanying it?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are there any, that are not <hi>by nature born in Sin,</hi> and become defiled and unclean thereby? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not <hi>Sanctification</hi> Seal'd in Baptiſm, whereby our Souls are cleanſed by his Spirit, as by the pouring on of Water? <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:37517:29"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not <hi>mortification</hi> or <hi>a death unto Sin</hi> one part of Sanctification? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.2, 3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can any improve their Baptiſm aright that do not <hi>dye unto ſin</hi> and dayly mortify their Corruptions? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. and 8.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And is not this aptly ſignifyed by pouring Water on the Perſon Baptized, as we caſt duſt on a body that is buried? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is not <hi>vivification</hi> or <hi>a riſing again <hi>unto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
                        </hi> the other part of Sanctification, and ſignify'd by coming from under the water of Baptiſm? <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† But though this be the inward Grace ſignify'd and Sealed by Baptiſm, yet is this Change wrought meerly by the outward waſhing? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is required of Perſons to be Baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repentance, whereby they forſake Sin, and Faith, whereby they ſtedfaſtly believe the promiſes of God made to them in that Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS Baptiſm to be adminiſtred to any Creatures ſave the Children of Men, or to any of them that are out of the viſible Church?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it not to be adminiſtred to all within the Church, without diſtinction of Nation, Sex, or Condition? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>May any Adult Perſon be admitted to Baptiſm with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Profeſſion of Faith and Repentance, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.15. or can they receive any ſaving benefit without thoſe Graces? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 41.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(1.) Is there not in <hi>repentance</hi> a deep ſenſe of Sin, Confeſſion of it to God, with ſhame, hatred, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for it? <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet is all this ſufficient without <hi>forſaking</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing <hi>Sin,</hi> in Heart and Life, and turning from it to the Lord? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And is not ſuch a <hi>repentance</hi> one thing that <hi>is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of Perſons that are to be Baptized?</hi> Mat. 3.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>(2.) Are we not to <hi>believe the promiſes</hi> of juſtifying and Sanctifying Grace, made in the new Covenant, and ſignifyed and Sealed in Baptiſm? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25, 26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:37517:29"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are there any ſuch <hi>promiſes</hi> without reſpect to Chriſt, or can we <hi>ſtedfaſtly believe</hi> them without <hi>Faith</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt, in and through whom they are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And is not ſuch a <hi>faith</hi> the other thing that <hi>is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Perſons that are to be Baptized?</hi> Acts 8.37.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why then are Infants Baptized, when by reaſon of their tender Age they cannot perform them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe they promiſe, them both by their ſureties; which promiſe when they come to Age, themſelves are bound to perform.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. WERE you capable of performing theſe when you were Baptized in Infancy, as you might have been, if you had been Baptized at Age?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is then the Baptiſm of Infants to be retained in the Church, and was our Baptiſm, in that tender Age, Lawful?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* If God extends his Covenant to the ſeed of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. may any deny them a Right to the Seal of that Covenant? <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7-10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> come upon the <hi>Gentiles, Gal.</hi> 3.14. and are not we graffed into the ſame Church that the <hi>Jews</hi> were broken off from? <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hath God then repealed his Grant made to <hi>Infants,</hi> or hath the Church fewer Priviledges, ſince Chriſt came, than it had before? <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not the Infants of Believers faederally Holy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. own'd as Covenant-ſervants, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.41, 42. and received as Diſciples? <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.42. <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was it not the Will of Chriſt, who is <hi>King of Kings,</hi> that whole <hi>Nations</hi> ſhould be diſcipled and Baptized? <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are Infants deny'd to be a part of <hi>Nations,</hi> or are they deny'd Birth-priviledges amongſt Men? <hi>Acts</hi> 22.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth not the Practice of the Univerſal Church in all Ages, agree to this and Confirm it? <hi>Acts</hi> 16.15, 33.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IF Infants they do not actually <hi>repent</hi> and <hi>believe,</hi> yet are they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>capable of coming under a <hi>promiſe</hi>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:37517:30"/>or engagement ſo to do? <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10-12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Though your engagement <hi>and promiſe</hi> was then declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by others, yet can you lay claim to the Benefits of the Covenant without ſtanding to that engagement your ſelves?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And now you are come to Age, do you not renew your Baptiſmal engagement, and are you not deſirous to be Confirmed therein by laying on of hands and Prayer? <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why was the Sacrament of the Lords Supper or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain'd?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the continual remembrance of the Sacrifice of the Death of Chriſt, and of the benefits which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the Lords Supper the other <hi>Sacrament</hi> and was it not <hi>Ordained</hi> by Chriſt, as well as Baptiſm? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was it <hi>Ordained,</hi> to be an unbloody Sacrifice or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for the Quick and the Dead? <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22, 25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Yet is it not an Euchariſt, or Spiritual Sacrifice of Thankſgiving and Goſpel Service? <hi>Mala.</hi> 1.11.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was not the <hi>death of Chriſt</hi> ſuch a Propitiatory <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi> Typifyed by all the bloody Sacrifices of Old? <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13, 14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Did He not bear the puniſhment of our iniquities, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6. and by ſhedding his blood make Atonement for them? <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not reconciliation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. Sanctification, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10. and Salvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. the <hi>Benefits</hi> which Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers receive by his death?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it a ſmall Mercy to have a memorial or <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi> of Chriſts death, when we are ſo apt to forget it? <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not <hi>remember</hi> his death, as a Hiſtory to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our knowledge; as a Goſpel to increaſe our Faith; and as an Example to promote our Patience? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is a bare Remembrance ſufficient, that is not affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, fiducial and operative? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16, 17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:37517:30"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is it ſufficient that we Remember him in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, once in our Lives or once in the Year?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt it not be a <hi>continual</hi> Remembrance, as often as we have opportunity, as we go often to our food? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25, 26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is this Ordinance Temporary to give place to others, as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sacraments were? <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Will it be <hi>continual</hi> and remain in the Church till Chriſt comes to Judgment? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the outward part, or Sign in the Lords ſupper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bread and Wine, which the Lord hath Commanded to be received.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. CAN <hi>Bread</hi> be more neceſſary to the Body, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.26. than Chriſt is to the Life of the Soul? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.33.57.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can <hi>Wine</hi> be more ſuited to the thirſt, than Chriſt is to the deſires of a Believer? <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.14.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Are not <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> moſt perfect in their Kind, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15. and apt to ſignifie a perfect Saviour?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Was not our Lord <hi>ſet forth</hi> for our Redemption, as the Elements are ſet apart for a Holy uſe? <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Doth not the breaking the bread and pouring out the Wine aptly Repreſent the torturing his body and ſhedding his bloud? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we have Life by Chriſt without Believing any more than our Natural Life can be maintained without Eating and Drinking? <hi>Habak.</hi> 2.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. HATH Chriſt who <hi>Commanded</hi> us to <hi>receive</hi> the Elements, bid us to lay them up, carry them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in proceſſion, or to adore them?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it ſufficient to receive one of theſe Elements with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other, when Chriſt <hi>has Commanded</hi> both <hi>to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived? Mat.</hi> 26.27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the imward part or thing ſignify'd?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Body and blood of Chriſt, which are verily and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37517:31"/>indeed taken and received by the Faithful in the Lords ſupper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. WHEN we are pertakers of Chriſts bloody death and the Benefits thereby are we not ſaid to receive his Body and Blood, or to eat his Fleſh and drink his Blood? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.56.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is this done after a Corporal or Carnal manner, as the <hi>Jews</hi> of Old and <hi>Papiſts</hi> now underſtand it? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.52.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are we to believe that the Subſtance of the Bread and Wine is changed into the Subſtance of Chriſts Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can we deny our Senſes, without deſtroying the Foundation of our Faith in Chriſt's Reſurrection and miracles? <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.39.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it Rational to Believe, that our Lord eat his Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Body with his own mouth, or that a true body can be whole in ten Thouſand places at once? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.61, 62.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is Not that which we eat and drink in the Sacrament called Bread and Wine after Conſecration? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is then the receiving Chriſts body and blood a Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtical thing, done only in Imagination and Pretence?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Do we <hi>verily</hi> and <hi>indeed</hi> pertake thereof in a Spiritual manner and by Faith? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.63.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Is this done by wicked and ungodly men, or by any but the <hi>Faithful</hi> or true Believers? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.54 —56.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are the Benefits, whereof we are made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers thereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſtrengthening and refreſhing of our ſouls by the Body and Blood of Chriſt, as our Bodies are by the Bread and Wine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. IS not the Lords Supper compar'd to a Feaſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7, 8. wherein the Benefits of Chriſts Death are the dainties, ſet forth by their excellency and variety? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can the bodies of men be more <hi>Strengthned</hi> at a Feaſt, than the Souls of Believers are <hi>Strengthned</hi> at the Lords Table? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.3.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:37517:31"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can there be a better means to <hi>Strengthen</hi> the habit of Grace in General to enable us to mortify Corruptions, overcome Temptations, bear our Burdens, and improve our Talents?</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>And doth not every particular Grace therein acted receive <hi>Strength</hi> by exerciſe? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can any Bodys be more <hi>refreſh't with Wine</hi> at a Feaſt, than the Souls of Believers are <hi>Comforted</hi> in the Lords Supper? <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. and 2.3, 4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can any thing be more <hi>reviving</hi> to a Soul, than to have Chriſt manifeſting his Love and Lovelineſs, in all the joys of his Salvation? <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.21, 22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is required of them who come to the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To examine themſelves whether they repent them truly of their former Sins, ſtedfaſtly purpoſing to lead a new Life, have a lively Faith in Gods mercy through Chriſt, with a thankful remembrance of his death; and be in Charity with all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>§. MAY any be admitted to the Lords Supper, who have not a Competency of Knowledge, to be ready for Confirmation, or are Scandalous and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious evil Livers? <hi>(Rubr. after Confirmation and before Confirmation.)</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is it ſufficient to have been approved and admitted by the Church, if we do not examine our Selves? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are not all Naturally unfit to diſcern the Lords Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or to delight in Communion with God? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Can any ruſh unprepared on this Ordinance, without diſhonour to God, and Judgment on themſelves? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27, 29.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Are there not certain Graces which accompany Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.9. which upon Examination may be known, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.10. eſpecially by the witneſs of the Spirit? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we be worthy Communicants without Sincere <hi>Repentance</hi> for our Sins paſt? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not examine, whether our ſorrow be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37517:32"/>and extended to Original Sin, and the Sins of our Hearts, and accompanied with the hatred and loathing of them? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can our repentance be true or our approach to the Sacrament right <hi>without full purpoſe of amendment?</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not examine whether our <hi>purpoſes</hi> are delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and without reſerve, and prevailing to an actual turning from all known ſin? <hi>Acts</hi> 11.23.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Dare you approach to the Lords Table without <hi>a lively Faith in Gods mercy through Chriſt?</hi> Joh. 6.35.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Is not Faith known upon Examination, by a great prizing of Chriſt and hungering after him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. and the victory and purity that follows upon it? <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we pertake of theſe Benefits at his Table, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> to God for them? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 43.4. and 63.6.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not examine this by our affections of Love and delight, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5, 6. and the yielding of our Selves to him for his benefits, in the paying our Vows? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.18.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>* Can we Communicate aright at a Feaſt of Love, without <hi>Charity</hi> and Love <hi>to all men? Eph.</hi> 5.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18-21.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Muſt we not examine this by our giving and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, doing good to all, with a peculiar delight in the Saints? <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23, 24. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Yes.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>† Is all our preparation ſufficient without a due care of our behaviour <hi>at,</hi> and <hi>after</hi> the receiving this Holy Sacrament? <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.12.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>No.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:37517:32"/>
            <head>Books Sold by <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible and Three-Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A Body of Practical Divinity conſiſting of above 176 Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on the leſſer Catechim compoſed by the Reverend Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> with a Supplement of ſome Sermons on ſeveral Texts of Scripture. By <hi>Tho. Watſon,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Miniſter of <hi>Stephens Walbrook, London:</hi> Recommended by 26 Miniſters to Maſters of Families and others. <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sermons and Diſcourſes on ſeveral Divine Subjects. By the late Reverend and Learned <hi>David Clerkson;</hi> B. D. and ſometime Fellow of <hi>Clare-Hall, Cambridge:</hi> With an Epiſtle of Mr. <hi>John How,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Mat. Mead,</hi> Folio.</item>
               <item>The Grace and Duty of being Spiritually-minded, declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Practically improved. By <hi>John Owen,</hi> D. D. in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Practical Expoſition on the 130 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> wherein the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of forgiveneſs of Sin is declared, the truth and reality of it aſſerted; and the Caſe of a Soul diſtreſſed with the guilt of Sin, and relieved by a diſcovery of forgiveneſs with God, is at large Diſcourſed. By <hi>John Owen,</hi> D. D. 4<hi>to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Expoſition with Practical Obſervations upon the Book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> By Mr. <hi>Alexander Niſbet</hi> Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel at <hi>Irwin,</hi> 4<hi>to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Several Diſcourſes concerning the Actual Providence of God: divided into 3 Parts, The firſt Treating of the Notion of it, Eſtabliſhing the Doctrine of it, opening the Principal Acts of it, Preſervation and Government of Created Beings; with the particular Acts by which it ſo preſerveth and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneth them: The Second concerning the Specialities of it, the unſearchable things of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Third Treats of the Hard Chapters, in which an attempt is made to Solve ſeveral appearances of difficulty in the Motions of Providence, and to vindicate the Juſtice, Wiſdom, and Holineſs of God, <hi>&amp;c. By John Collinges,</hi> D. D. 4<hi>to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Intercourſes of Divine Love betwixt Chriſt and the Church, or the Particular Believing Soul, as Metaphorically expreſſed by <hi>Solomon</hi> in Firſt and Second Chapters of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> opened and applied in ſeveral Sermons; in which the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies of Chriſt, the Yearnings of his Bowels towards Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, under various Circumſtances; the workings of their Hearts towards, and in Communion with Him. With many other Goſpel propoſitions of great import to Souls are hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. By <hi>John Collinges,</hi> D. D. in 2 Volumes, 4<hi>to.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Theological Diſcourſes in 2 Parts. The Firſt containing
<pb facs="tcp:37517:33"/>Eight Letters and three Sermons concerning the Bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Trinity. The Second Diſcourſes and Sermons on ſeveral Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. By <hi>John Wallis,</hi> D. D. Profeſſor of Geometry in <hi>Oxford,</hi> Quarto.</item>
               <item>A Paraphraſe on the New Teſtament with Notes Doctrinal and Practical; by plainneſs and brevity fitted to the uſe of Religious Families, in their dayly reading of the Scriptures; and of the younger and poorer ſort of Scholars and Miniſters, who want fuller helps. With an Advertiſement of Difficulties in the <hi>Revelation.</hi> By the late Reverend Mr. <hi>Rich. Baxter.</hi> The Second Edition Corrected. To which is added at the end, Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> account of his Notes on ſome Particular Texts, for which he was Impriſoned, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richard Baxters</hi> dying Thoughts upon <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. written for his own uſe in the latter times of his Corporal pains and weakneſs. The Second Edition, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Family altar erected to the honour of the Eternal God: or a Solemn eſſay to promote the Worſhip of God in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Houſes: Being ſome Meditations on <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.2, 3. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the beſt Entail, or dying Parents, living hopes for their Surviving Children, grounded upon the Covenant of Grace. By <hi>O. Heywood</hi> Miniſter, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A New Creature, or a ſhort diſcourſe opening the Nature, Properties, and Neceſſity of the great Work of the New Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation upon the Souls of Men. By <hi>O. Heywood</hi> an unworthy Miniſter of the Goſpel, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spiritual-ſongs or Songs of Praiſe to Almighty God upon Several occaſions; Together with the Song of Songs, which is <hi>Solomons,</hi> firſt turned. then Paraphraſed in Engliſh Verſe: To which may be added Penitential Cries, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sacramental Hymns Collected (chiefly) out of ſuch Paſſages of the New Teſtament as contain the moſt Suitable matter of Divine Praiſes in the Celebration of the Lords Supper; to which is added one Hymn relating to Baptiſm, and another to the Miniſtry. By <hi>J. Boyſe</hi> Miniſter in <hi>Dublin, Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Collection of Divine Hymns upon ſeveral occaſions, ſuited to our Common Tunes, for the uſe of devout Chriſtians in Singing forth the Praiſes of God, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Six Centeries of Select Hymns and Spiritual Songs, Collected out of the Bible; together with a Catechiſm: The <hi>Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> and a Catalogue of Vertuous Women. By <hi>William Barton,</hi> A. M. Twelves.</item>
               <item>Family Hymns gathered (moſtly) out of the beſt Tranſlations of <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms. By <hi>Mat. Henry</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Cheſter, Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
